Alright, I want we get started,
好的，我想我们开始了，
you know people want to turn on the camera again
人们想再次打开摄像机，
or well it be great used to create sort of class atmosphere,
它可以很好地创造班级氛围，
it's the best we can.
这是我们能做的最好的。
Okay, so this is,
好的，这是，
we're going to talk today about this paper,
今天我们要讨论这篇论文，
you know the benefits and cost of writing a UNIX kernel in a high-level language,
使用用高级语言编写 UNIX 内核的好处和成本，
you know, this is basically paper that was partly written because of 6.S081 or 6.828,
这篇论文编写部分原因是因为 6.S081 或 6.828 ，
and there's the paper that you know we've written,
这篇论文是由我们编写的，
you know Robert and I,
Robert 和我，
and that the main person was a main lead was Cody Cutler,
但主要人物是 Cody Cutler ，
who was a TA this class many many times.
他在这门课上当过很多次助教。
It's always a little bit,
这总是有一点，
you know I don't really enjoy
我不是特别喜欢
actually particularly talking about papers that we worked on ourselves,
谈论我们自己编写的论文，
but you know this paper came about basically 6.S081 or 6.828,
但是这篇论文基本上来自 6.S081 或 6.828 ，
and so I'm gonna use some slides this time
所以这次我要用一些幻灯片，
instead of actually writing on a whiteboard.
而不是在白板上书写。
And so really the source of this paper is this question
所以这篇论文的真正来源就是这个问题，
in what language should you write a kernel.
应该用什么语言编写内核。
And this is a question that many, many of you asked
这是你们很多人都问过的问题，
where you know students in the past 6.828 graduate asked many many many times,
在过去的 6.828 毕业生中问了很多次，
apparently you know because you know you have bugs in the operating system or your kernel
因为你的操作系统或内核中有 bug ，
and you're like well, if I had written this other language,
你会说，如果我使用另一种语言编写，
then you know maybe I would not have those bugs.
也许我就不会有那些 bug 了。
So this is a question that often comes about
所以这是一个经常出现的问题，
and it turns out you know in the operating system community at large,
事实上，在整个操作系统社区中，
you know this is a hotly debated question,
这是一个争论不休的问题，
but not that many facts, you could actually make a sort of any informed discussion.
但事实并不多，你可以进行任何知情的讨论。
And what we'll see at this at the end of this lecture,
我们将在这节课结束时看到，
during this lecture or you as you read the paper,
在课程中或你读论文时，
I know we don't really have a crisp answer to this question,
我知道我们对这个问题没有明确的答案，
but we have sort of this paper contributes you know a bunch of data,
但是我们这篇论文贡献了很多数据，
that you know allows you to have a little bit more of an in-depth discussion
可以让你有更深入的讨论，
about what is a good programming language for the kernel.
关于什么是内核的好的编程语言。
So that was really the original of this paper,
这就是这篇论文的原创之处，
and and so we're, and the source you know of this paper is basically you guys.
基本上这篇论文的来源就是你们。
So, try to answer the question,
那么，为了回答这个问题，
we wrote a new kernel,
我们编写了一个新的内核，
and we did it in the language with automatic memory management
并且我们用具有自动内存管理的语言，
that means with garbage collector,
这意味着有垃圾收集器，
so you don't actually have to call free,
所以你不需要调用 free ，
you know and avoid a class bugs,
可以避免一类 bug ，
so that's one of the properties at a high level language typically has,
这是高级语言通常具有的属性之一，
and so we wanted to have picked a language that has that,
所以，我们希望选择一种具有这种特性的语言，
and we followed basically traditional monolithic Unix organization,
我们基本上遵循了传统的 Unix 结构，
we could do a fair comparison.
我们可以做一个公平的比较。
And in fact some way you could think about what we built is something like xv6,
在某种程度上，你可以认为我们构建的是类似于 xv6 的东西，
much much more, more features and more high performance.
功能更多，性能更高。
I mean, as you know,
我的意思是，正如你知道的，
xv6 has all kinds of chronic algorithms or linear search, type algorithms,
xv6 有各种慢性算法或线性搜索、类型算法，
and of course if you want to achieve high performance,
当然，如果你想实现高性能，
you can't have those.
你不能有这些。
And so that was the original, this paper in the original,
所以，这就是论文的来源，
why we built Biscuit trying to answer that question
为什么我们构建了 Biscuit 试图回答这个问题，
or at least shed some light.
或者至少给我们一些启示。
First, I'm going to talk a little bit about sort of more general background,
首先，我要讨论一下更一般的背景，
I got a lot of questions over email,
我通过电子邮件得到很多问题，
we're trying to get a little bit more context,
我们正试图获得更多的背景信息，
and then I will dive into Biscuit in more more detail,
然后我会更详细地讨论 Biscuit ，
feel free to jump in with questions in any particular point of time,
任何时间都可以随意提出问题，
here as you know this paper was motivated by questions you asked,
正如你所知道的，这篇论文的动机是你们提出的问题，
and so you know please please ask keep asking questions.
所以，请继续问问题。
So, as you can just do,
所以，正如你可以做的那样，
sort of the setting of this paper is a lot of kernels are written in C,
这篇论文的设置是很多内核都是用 C 语言写的，
and you know xv6 is written in C, you're programming in C,
xv6 是用 C 语言写的，你使用 C 语言编写程序，
but most popular kernels that you see on your desktop or your phone are written in C,
你在桌面或手机上看到的大多数流行内核都是用 C 语言编写的，
Windows Linux Linux to all the various forms of BSDs.
Windows Linux 以及所有各种形式的 BSD 。
And, and the reason the written or written in C is that,
用 C 语言编写的原因是，
C provides a lot of control as you've seen in the labs,
C 提供了很多控制，正如你在实验中看到的，
yeah, complete control for memory allocation and freeing,
完全控制内存分配和释放，
there's almost no implicit code,
几乎没有隐式代码，
you know you can almost imagine when you're reading the C code,
你几乎可以想象，当你阅读 C 代码的时候，
what the corresponding RISC-V instructions are,
对应的 RISC-V 指令是什么，
you have direct access to memory,
你可以直接访问内存，
you can read or write you know the PTE bits you know or the register of a devices,
你可以读写 PTE 位或者设备寄存器，您知道您知道的PTE位或设备的寄存器，
and you know C itself [] very few dependencies,
而且 C 语言本身有很少的依赖，
you know there's no large runtime that you actually have to have,
你并不需要很大的运行时，
to be able to run a C program,
为了能够运行 C 程序，
you can almost run almost immediately on bare hareware.
你几乎可以直接在裸硬件上运行。
And you've seen that once xv6 boots,
你已经看到一旦 xv6 启动，
you know it's basically a few lines of assembly
先是几行汇编代码，
and then basically you're running C code.
然后你就是在运行 C 代码。
But there are all the good virtues of C
但是这些都是 C 语言优点，
and one reason that we like C a lot.
也是我们非常喜欢 C 的一个原因。
But C also has some downsides,
但是 C 也有一些缺点，
you know it has been proven over the last few decades,
在过去的几十年里已经被证明了，
that writing security C code is difficult,
写安全的 C 代码很难，
you know there are types of bugs that can, you can often be exploited
有几种类型的 bug ，经常会被利用，
whether it is buffer overruns,
无论是缓冲区溢出，
which are probably the most well-known one you're writing behind the past,
这可能是在过去最广为人知的问题，
an array bound or you're writing you know below your stack,
一个数组绑定，或者你正在堆下面写，
use-after-free bugs, you know where you know the free of memory, but it's still in use,
use-after-free bug ，你释放了内存，但是它仍在使用，
and so when somebody scribbles on it
所以当有人在上面乱写的时候，
and you know scribble something bad on it,
在上面乱写一些不好的东西，
and generally you know when threads are sharing memory
通常情况下，线程共享内存时，
is typically difficult to decide you know what actually memory can be freed.
很难决定哪些内存可以释放。
Some of these bugs, you know don't really show up that,
有些 bug ，并不会真的出现在那里，
you know some of the bug manifest itself explicitly xv6, some less,
一些 bug 明确地体现在 xv6 中，一些较少，
so you know, you know xv6 very little dynamic memory allocation,
xv6 的动态内存分配非常少，
you're almost after being sort of pre allocated [right up front],
你几乎是已经预先分配好了，
a buffer overruns usually have free bugs do show up.
缓冲区溢出通常会出现释放 bug 。
So, in fact you know if you look at CVEs,
事实上，如果你看一看 CVEs ，
you know these are you know there's a website
有一个网站，
where there's an organization that keeps control,
有一个组织保持控制，
that checks and keeps a record of all of the security exploits,
检查和记录所有安全漏洞，
and investigate that you'll find that in 2017 when we were doing this paper,
调查一下，你会发现，在 2017 年我们做这篇论文的时候，
that there were 40 Linux kernel bugs,
有 40 个 Linux 内核 bug ，
that can actually lead to an attacker running take complete control over the machine.
会导致攻击者完全控制机器。
Clearly, you know those are serious bugs
显然，那些是严重的 bug ，
and those bugs came out of buffer overruns
这些 bug 来自于缓冲区溢出，
and other types of memory safety bugs.
以及其他类型的内存安全 bug 。
So you know it's sort of too bad,
所以这太糟糕了，
you know that if you write code in C,
如果你用 C 语言写代码，
you know that actually is hard,
很难做到，
even for people that do that professionally and to actually get this right.
即使是专业人士也很难做到这一点。
And of course you know, I'm sure you've seen this in the lab,
当然，我相信你在实验里见过这个，
you know probably certainly I remember from some of the the Piazza questions,
也许，我记得在 Piazza 上的一些问题，
you know the number if you run into use-after-free bugs,
你们遇到 use-after-free bug 的次数，
you know in particular in the copy-on-write lab,
特别是在写入时复制实验里，
they showed up a bunch of times.
它们出现了很多次。
So yeah so, one reason that a high-level language would be attractive is that,
所以，高级语言吸引人的一个原因是，
a high-level language that provides memory safety,
高级语言提供了内存安全，
and so all these bugs that CVE exploits
所以，所有 CVE 披露的 bug ，
that I mentioned on the previous slide
我在上一张幻灯片中提到的，
would not be would not be possible,
将会是不可能的，
you know could use you know they if they happen,
如果它们发生了，
they either would result in a panic,
它们要么会导致 panic ，
you know, because you know the runtime which would say,
因为运行时会说，
like, oh you're writing passed away, you can't do that,
你要写的东西已经不在了，你不能那样做，
or you know you just couldn't manifest itself at all,
或者根本不能表现出来，
because the language wouldn't allow you to write that kind of code.
因为语言不会允许你编写这样的代码。
So there are of course other benefits to a high-level language,
高级语言当然还有其他好处，
you know which often is also mentioned you know by you know students in this class,
这门课上的学生也经常提到，
when they're doing labs,
当他们在做实验时，
in addition to type safety,
除了类型安全，
you know there's automatic memory management with garbage collector,
还有具有垃圾收集器的自动内存管理，
so freeing is easy,
所以释放是很简单的，
you don't have to think about it,
你不用考虑它，
the garbage collector does all the work for you,
垃圾收集器会帮你做所有的工作，
it's good for concurrency,
它对并发性有好处，
you know it has good abstractions,
它有很好的抽象性，
you know it's like Go its interfaces or some other classes or some other form of,
比如 Go 它的接口或其他一些类或其他形式的，
you know forces you or encourage you to actually write modular code.
这会鼓励你编写模块化代码。
The downsides and you might be wondering like,
不好的一面，你可能会想，
oh if there's so many upsides to high-level languages,
如果高级语言有这么多好处，
you know why not,
为什么不，
you know why is xv6 not written in you know Java Go Python or whatever,
为什么 xv6 不是用 Java Go Python 或其他什么来写，
and the reason is you know the or Linux,
原因是， Linux ，
you know the reason is there's poor performance,
原因是它的性能很差，
you know there's a cost to actually a high-level language,
高级语言是要付出代价的，
sometimes this is referred to as the high-level language tax.
有时这被称为高级语言税。
And you know these are basically you know if you do an array bounds, array index,
这些是，如果你做一个数组界限，数组索引，
you know you have to check the bounds,
你必须检查边界，
you know you have to check nil-pointers,
你必须检查空指针，
and they have more expensive cast,
它们有更昂贵的转换，
and you know garbage collection itself is also not free,
垃圾收集也不是免费的，
you know there's gonna be some cycles spent tracking down
要花几个周期来追踪，
which objects are free, which are allocated, then you know that's a cost.
哪些对象是空闲的，哪些是分配的，这是也是损失。
So that's you know from the performance side
所以这是从性能方面，
and a lot of the paper focuses on this.
很多论文都集中在这一点。
And then in principle you know often I mean
然后原则上，我的意思是，
it's perceived as a sort of incompatibility with Linux kernel programming,
它被认为是与 Linux 内核编程的不兼容，
you know no direct memory access,
没有直接的内存访问，
you know, because the principal could know a violate type safety,
因为原则可能知道违反了类型安全，
no hand-written assembly
没有手写汇编语言，
and you need some hand-written assembly in the kernel,
你需要在内核中使用一些手写汇编语言，
whereas the context switch between two threads
在两个线程之间的上下文切换，
or to get off the ground when the machine boots,
或者在机器启动时顺利开始，
in you know often,
通常情况下，
you know the language may have a particular plan for concurrency or parallelism
语言可能有一个特定的并发或并行的计划，
that might not line up with the plan that the kernel needs work concurrency parallelism,
可能与内核需要的并发并行不一致，
we've seen for example and a scheduling lecture,
我们已经看到，比如在调度课程中，
you know one thread passes a lock to another thread,
一个线程将锁传递给另一个线程，
where you know there's a couple you know there's patterns of concurrency management
有几种并发管理的模式，
that are sort of unusual and usual programs,
这些都是不普通或普通的程序，
but they do show up in, in kernels.
但它们确实出现在内核中。
So, so the goal basically of this you know paper was
所以，这个论文的目标是，
to sort of measure the high-level language trade-offs,
衡量高级语言的权衡，
explore the total effects of using high-level language instead of C,
探索使用高级语言代替 C 语言的总体效果，
you know both in terms of a safety program ability,
不仅是在安全编程能力方面，
but also for performance cost.
而且在性能成本方面。
And of course if you'd like to do this, this kind of experiment,
当然，如果你想做这个实验，
you know you need to do that sort of a production grade kernel,
你需要做那种生产级的内核，
you can't do that on xv6,
你不能在 xv6 上做到这一点，
because it's so slow that basically you probably won't learn anything,
因为它太慢了，你可能什么都学不到，
you know it's a program that was written slow in C,
这是一个用 C 语言写得很慢的程序，
you're written slow in Go,
你用 Go 也写得很慢，
you know doesn't really tell you much about you know the C versus Go question,
这并不能告诉你很多关于 C 对 Go 的问题，
it just says like well xv6 slow.
它只是说 xv6 很慢。
And so you want to do that in a more high performance you know oriented kernel
所以你想要在一个更高性能的内核，
or the kernel was designed for high performance.
或者内核是为高性能而设计的。
And so you're you know one of the things that are surprising,
所以你知道有一件事是令人惊讶的，
because like many of you ask this [] ask this
因为你们中的许多人问到这个，
and I would imagine well this question must be answered in the literature,
我想这个问题一定会在文献中得到回答，
and you know it turns out that actually isn't,
事实证明这并不是，
it is there's quite a number of studies that look into the question
有很多的研究这个问题，
of high-level language trade-offs in the context of user programs,
关于高级语言在用户程序中的权衡的问题，
and, but you know as you know the kernel is quite a bit different from user programs,
但是内核和用户程序有很大的不同，
for example memory management, careful memory management is really important,
比如仔细的内存管理是非常重要的，
this different types of concurrency may be slightly different,
这种不同类型的并发性可能略有不同，
so we want to do it in the context of a kernel.
所以我们想在内核中做这件事。
And we don't actually really find any sort of papers really answer this question,
我们没有找到任何论文真正回答这个问题，
the closer you could come to is,
你能接近的是，
there you know there are many kernels written in high-level language,
有很多内核是用高级语言编写的，
you know there's a long history of doing that,
这样做已经有很长的历史了，
they're dating back even to sort of the early [] machines,
甚至可以追溯到早期的机器，
and you know but many of the sort of recent versions of these kernels
但是很多这些内核的最新版本，
are not really written with the idea of evaluating this high-level language tax question,
并不是根据评估高级语言税问题的想法来做的，
but really to explore new OS designs and new OS architectures,
而是真正探索新的操作系统设计和新的操作系统架构，
and so none of them really measured directly,
所以它们没有一个是直接评估，
you know sort of head to head comparison,
比如面对面的比较，
and keep the structure the same,
保持结构不变，
so you can really focus on this issue of the language
所以你可以真正专注于语言的问题，
as opposed to some other issues.
而不是其他问题。
In fact we used to read you know some of these papers actually in the past.
事实上，我们过去读过一些论文。
So, you know there's one reason may be that,
所以，有一个原因可能是，
there's not a lot of work that actually answers,
没有太多的工作回答，
a ton of papers not answer this question is,
很多论文没有回答这个问题，
it's actually tricky to do it,
做这件事是很困难的，
basically if you really do it right,
如果你真的想做它，
you know you want to compare with a production grade C kernel,
想和一个 C 编写的生产级别的内核进行比较，
that means something like Linux or something that Windows whatever,
比如 Linux 或 Windows 之类的东西，
but then you have to build a production grade kernel
然后你必须构建一个产品级别的内核，
and you know clearly for a small team that is very hard to do,
当然，对于一个小团队来说，这是很难做到的，
you know there's lots of lots of Linux kernel developers,
你知道有很多 Linux 内核开发者，
make many many changes you know week by week day by day
做了很多修改，一周又一周，一天又一天，
and so it's going to be hard to
所以很难做到，
you know to do the same thing
做同样的事情，
and build an equivalent you know type of thing,
构建一个同类型的东西，
so you have to settle for something slightly less than.
所以你只能满足于稍微低于。
So the best we could do or the best we could come up to do is
所以，我们能做的最好的是，
build a high-level build a kernel on the high-level language,
构建一个高级语言的内核，
you know keep most of the important aspects of same as Linux,
保持大部分重要方面与 Linux 相同，
optimized performance,
优化性能，
roughly optimized performance until it's roughly similar to Linux,
优化性能，直到与 Linux 大致相似，
you know even though maybe it's not identically exactly identical features,
即使它可能不是完全相同的特性，
but it gets into the same ballpark
但它进入了同样的范围内，
and then measured high-level language trade-offs.
然后评估高级语言的权衡。
And of course you know the risk you know this approach is that
当然，这种方法的风险是，
you know the kernel that we built you know actually is slightly different than Linux,
我们构建的内核实际上与 Linux 略有不同，
you know it's not gonna be exactly like Linux
它不会和 Linux 完全一样，
and so you've gotta be very careful when drawing any conclusions.
所以当你得出任何结论时，必须非常小心。
And you know and this is one reason
这是一个原因，
why you can still get a really crystal clear answer,
为什么我们仍然可以得到一个相当清晰的答案，
that is the question that basically this paper proposes,
这就是这篇论文提出的问题，
but we can hopefully get a little bit more deeper insight
但我们希望能获得更深层次的洞察力，
than basically saying almost nothing about it.
而不是基本上什么都不说。
Is this makes sense, so far, any questions?
这能理解吗，到目前为止，有什么问题吗？
That's sort of the context of this paper,
这就是这篇论文的背景，
and you know why we gone to do it.
以及为什么我们这么做。
Okay so, if there's no questions,
好的，如果没有问题，
I'd like to talk a little bit more about the methodology.
我想多谈一点关于方法论的问题。
So, so basically you know the sort of setup is
所以，基本的设置是，
here on the left side, you know we have our is gonna be Biscuit,
在左边，有我们的 Biscuit ，
you know, we're gonna, in our particular case,
我们要，在我们的情况中，
we wrote for this paper the kernel in Go,
我们为这篇论文使用 Go 编写的内核，
it provides roughly a similar subset of the system calls Linux provides,
它提供了与 Linux 的系统调用大致相同的子集，
but you know the way to,
你知道它们的方式，
but they have same arguments,
它们有相同的参数，
you know the same calling interfaces.
相同的的调用接口。
And we run basically the same applications on top of that interface,
我们在接口上运行相同的应用程序，
so you know one of the applications and Nginx which is a web server,
其中一个应用程序是网络服务器 Nginx ，
and so the idea is that
所以我们的想法是，
you know we're on the same application both on Biscuit and Linux,
我们在 Biscuit 和 Linux 上使用相同的应用程序，
you know the application will generate the same system call trace with exactly the same arguments
应用程序使用完全相同的参数生成相同的系统调用[跟踪]，
and both Biscuit and Linux you know perform all the necessary operations
Biscuit 和 Linux 执行所有必须的操作，
that are invoked by those system calls,
由这些系统调用引起的，
and then we can sort of look at you know
然后我们可以看一下
the difference is basically between you know the high-level language kernel and Linux,
高级语言内核和 Linux 之间的区别，
and sort of talk about like you know what are the trade-offs.
并讨论一下什么是权衡。
And so after the core of the methodology
所以在方法论之后，
and again because Linux and Biscuit are not going to be exactly identical,
因为 Linux 和 Biscuit 不会完全相同，
you know there's gonna be some differences,
这里会有一些不同，
but you know we spend a lot of time in this
但是我们在这里花了很多时间，
trying to you know make comparison as far as possible,
尽可能地进行比较，
wherever possible we could think of making it.
尽可能想办法做成它。
So a lot of you ask this question
你们中的很多人都会问这个问题，
which high-level language use,
使用哪种高级语言，
you know for this kind of work
对于这种工作，
and you know we pick Go and for a couple of reasons,
我们选择 Go ，出于几个原因，
it is a statically compiled language,
它是一种静态编译语言，
so unlike Python, there's no interpreter,
所以与 Python 不同，这里没有解释器，
and the reason that we like static compiled,
这是我们喜欢静态编译的原因，
because we've basically compiles actually high performance code,
因为我们可以编译高性能的代码，
in fact the particular Go compiler is pretty good.
实际上， Go 编译器是相当不错的。
So basically you know sort of high performance language,
所以它是一种高性能的语言，
furthermore, Go design is actually intended for system programming
此外， Go 的设计是为系统编程的，
you know kernels or for system programming,
内核或系统编程，
so that could be a good match.
所以它是一个很好的选择。
As an example, you know aspect of why it's a good system programming,
举个例子，为什么它是一个好的系统编程语言，
it's actually easy to call assembly or other foreign code,
它很容易调用汇编或其他外来代码，
it has good support for concurrency, quite flexible.
它对并发有很好的支持，非常方便。
And then another reason that we wanted to use it,
然后另一个我们想要使用它的原因，
because it has a garbage collector,
因为它有一个垃圾收集器，
one of the things that you think about a high-level language,
关于高级语言需要考虑的一件事，
and one of the virtues of a high-level languages
高级语言的优点之一，
that you don't have to do memory management,
你不需要进行内存管理，
and garbage collectors typically in a central role in the,
垃圾收集器通常是关键角色，
yeah, provides a central role in a sort of memory management story.
在内存管理中提供关键角色。
By the time we started this paper,
当我们开始写这篇论文的时候，
or we started this project,
或者我们开始这个项目的时候，
Rust was not very popular
Rust 不是很流行，
or Rust was not very stable and mature at that point,
或者 Rust 还不是很稳定和成熟，
and the actually could write a real kernel,
它可以写一个真正的内核，
in a retrospect now,
现在回想一下，
you do it again,
如果你再做一次，
you know you may write it in Rust,
你可以使用 Rust 来写，
because it also designs for system programming,
因为它也是为系统编程设计的，
it has a small runtime, produces good code,
它有一个很小的运行时，可以产生好的代码，
although one thing that
尽管有一件事，
actually might still make it very [instinct] to go for Go is that,
可能仍然会让人[本能地]去尝试的是，
Rust takes the starting assumption
Rust 首先假设，
that that if you want high performance systems programs,
如果你想要高性能系统程序，
then you can't do that with a garbage collector.
那么你不能使用垃圾收集器。
And in fact a Rust type system is set up in a very clever way
事实上， Rust 类型系统以一种非常聪明的方式，
and a very interesting way,
和一种非常有趣的方式设置的，
so that actually the garbage collector is not necessary.
所以垃圾收集器是不必要的。
And in some ways, we were interested in answering this question,
在某些方面，我们对回答这个问题很感兴趣，
what is the cost of garbage collection in a high-level language,
在高级语言中进行垃圾收集的成本是多少，
you know on kernel programming
关于内核编程，
and it is really impossible to use or what does that cost,
它的成本是多少，
in some ways, you know Rust sidestep that question
在某些方面， Rust 绕过了这个问题，
and just like you know use a language without garbage collection,
使用一种没有垃圾回收的语言，
you haven't to think about this particular cost.
你不必须考虑这个成本。
Any questions about this,
关于这个有什么问题吗，
in terms of the programming language we decided to use.
关于我们决定使用的编程语言方面。
Lots of email questions related to this topic.
许多邮件里的问题与这个主题有关。
This is a theoretical question,
这是一个理论问题，
that maybe doesn't have an immediate answer,
可能没有直接的答案，
but if the Linux kernel were to be written on Rust not Go,
但是如果编写 Linux 内核使用 Rust 而不是 Go ，
and like optimized in the same capacity,
在相同的能力下进行优化，
would it be able to achieve higher performance?
它是否能够实现更高的性能？
Than, than the Go concurrency?
比 Go 的并发吗？
Than C, like a Linux C kernel.
比 C ，比如 C 编写的 Linux 内核。
I doubt it will be,
我怀疑它会，
okay, hard to know, just speculation, correct,
好的，很难知道，只是猜测，
because we haven't done this experiment,
因为我们做有过这个实验，
in my senses, you know would be not higher performance than C,
在我看来，不会比 C 有更高的性能，
but you know probably roughly the same ballpark.
但可能大致相同。
Because C so low-level,
因为 C 是低级语言，
you can assume whatever you do in Rust,
你可以假设你在 Rust 里所做的，
you could also have done in C.
你也可以用 C 来做。
Does that make sense?
这能理解吗？
Yes, thank you.
好的，谢谢。
Okay.
好的。
Okay, so let's move on them,
好的，我们开始吧，
unless there are any other further questions about this,
除非对于这个还有任何其他问题，
and again feel free to interrupt
再说一次，请随意打断，
and you know there's a bit of a discussion based lecture,
这里一节基于讨论的课程，
and so it was intended to stimulate intellectual interests,
它的目的是激发智力和兴趣，
so you jump in if you have anything to think about this topic.
所以，如果你对这个话题有什么想说的，可以加入进来。
So actually before you know maybe the question I want to ask,
所以在我想问的问题之前，
maybe I'll come back to that at the end of the lecture,
也许我会在课程结束时回来看，
closer to the end of the lecture.
课程快结束的时候。
Partly you know the whole reason we ought to use high-level languages
在一定程度上，我们使用高级语言
to avoid sort of class of bugs
来避免某种类型的 bug ，
and one question you should ask yourself,
你应该问自己一个问题，
where bugs you know in the labs that you had that would have been avoided,
你在实验中出现的哪种 bug 是可以避免的，
if you had a high level language.
如果你使用高级语言。
You know, so you know think back,
所以回想一下，
you know I'm sure you can come up with some bugs,
我相信你能想出一些 bug ，
that you cost you a lot of time and a lot of pain,
花了你很多时间和痛苦，
and you could ask yourself those kind of bugs,
你可以问自己这些 bug ，
you know if we if the xv6 where we run into labs
如果我们在实验中的 xv6 ，
would be done in another high-level programming language,
用另一种高级编程语言来完成，
would have life would be a lot easier,
会让生活变得容易很多，
would you have a lot more spare time to do other things.
让你有更多的空闲时间做其他事情。
So let's keep that question in your head
所以我们带着这个问题，
and you know hopefully return to that at the end of the lecture.
在课程结束时回到这个问题上来。
But if you have opinions right away, that's fine too.
但是如果你现在有想法，也没问题。
Okay, so let me talk a little bit about Biscuit,
好的，让我说一下 Biscuit ，
and you know sort of works
其中的工作，
in sort of surprises where the things,
一些惊讶的事情，
that we ran into while building Biscuit things,
我们在构建 Biscuit 过程中的东西，
that we anticipated in some things that we actually did not anticipate.
我们遇到一些没有预料到的东西。
So the user programs,
所以用户程序，
there's a classic kernel,
这里有一个传统内核，
a monolithic kernel in the same way to Linux or xv6's,
一个与 Linux 或 xv6 相同的宏内核，
and so there's user space and kernel space,
所以这里有用户空间和内核空间，
user space programs are
用户空间程序是，
you know whatever your compiler GCC
比如你的编译器 GCC ，
or in our speaking of paper it's mostly a web server,
或者在我们的论文中，它是一个网络服务器，
and some other benchmarks.
以及其他一些基准。
And the user programs are actually all written in C,
用户程序都是用 C 语言编写的，
although it could be principal in any language,
尽管它可以是任何语言编写的，
you know since they're just a benchmark,
因为它们只是一个基准，
we took C versions,
我们采用 C 语言版本，
and most of the programs are multi-thread,
并且多数程序都是多线程的，
so unlike in xv6 where basically there's one thread per user program,
所以，与 xv6 中每个用户程序只有一个线程不同，
in Biscuit, actually support multiple user level threads.
在 Biscuit 中，支持多个用户线程。
And basically for every user level thread,
对于每个用户线程，
there's corresponding kernel thread in kernel,
在内核中都有相应的内核线程，
and this kernel threads are actually implemented by Go itself
这些内核线程是由 Go 实现的，
and Go calls these Go routines,
Go 调用 Go 例程，
you can think about Go routines just as ordinary threads
你可以把 Go 例程看作普通线程，
in the same way that xv6 has and the kernel has threads,
与 xv6 相同的方式，内核具有线程，
the Go routines are similar,
Go 协程是类似的，
the main difference it correctly is that,
主要的区别是，
in xv6 you know the threads are implemented by the kernel itself,
在 xv6 中，线程是由内核实现的，
and in this case you know Go runtime basically provides,
在这种情况下，是由 Go 运行时提供的，
the Go runtime schedules them,
Go 运行时调度它们，
Go runtime has support for things like sleep wakeup or condition variables,
Go 运行时支持睡眠唤醒或条件变量，
there's lots of different sleep wakeup,
有不同的睡眠唤醒，
but there's some condition variable synchronization mechanism,
但有一些条件变量同步机制，
and there's a whole bunch of other you know things primitive,
还有很多原语，
and Go runtime just provided by the Go language itself,
Go 运行时 Go 语言本身提供，
and you have not been implemented by Biscuit itself,
不是由 Biscuit 本身实现的，
we just get them from the Go runtime.
我们只是从 Go 运行时获得它们。
The Go runtime itself runs directly on the bare hardware.
GO 运行时本身直接在裸硬件上运行。
And, I'll talk a little bit about that more in the lecture,
我会在课程中更多地谈到这一点，
but like so you think about this is the machine boots,
但你可以认为这是机器启动，
you know the first thing it actually boots to Go runtime,
第一件事就是启动到 Go 运行时，
does it cause a lot of complications,
这带来了很多复杂情况，
because Go runtime that normally runs in user space as user level program
因为通常 Go 运行时作为用户程序运行在用户空间，
and assumes that the kernel there's a kernel there,
假设有一个内核，
we can ask some services,
我们可以请求一些服务，
for example, needs to allocate memory to, for its heap.
比如，需要为其堆分配内存。
And so there's a little bit of, all talk a little bit about,
所以这里有一些，
that there's a little bit of shim code,
有一些垫片代码，
the Biscuit has to basically trick you know Go runtime
Biscuit 用来欺骗 Go 进行时，
into believing that it runs on top of the operating system,
使其相信它运行在操作系统之上，
even though it's running on bare hardware,
即使它是在裸硬件上运行，
and basically get the boot.
获得启动。
And then the kernel itself, you know it's very similar, you think xv6,
然后内核本身跟 xv6 非常相似，
think there's a model,
想象有一种模型，
except it's a little bit more elaborate and more high performance,
不过它更复杂，性能更高，
it has some virtual memory system,
它有虚拟内存系统，
you know that for example implements mmap lab you're doing this week,
比如，你这周要做的 mmap 实验，
it has a file system,
它有一个文件系统，
like there's more high performance file system,
有更高性能的文件系统，
it has a couple of drivers,
它有一些驱动，
you know it has a disk drive
它有磁盘驱动，
and it has a network driver, it has a network stack,
它有网络驱动，有网络堆栈，
so it will be more complete,
所以它会更完整，
and when you can see that is, it has like 58 system calls,
你可以看到，它有大概 58 个系统调用，
you know like I can't remember how much xv6 has,
我记不清 xv6 有多少了，
but [startling] the order of 18 19 or something like that.
但应该是 18 或 19 个左右。
And the total number of launch code is 28000,
启动代码的总数是 28000 个，
you know xv6 is like not in, I think below 10000,
xv6 我想是在 10000 以下，
so you know there's more features.
所以这里有更多功能。
Any questions about sort of this high-level overview?
关于这个高级别的概述，有什么问题吗？
Oh, sorry I wanted to ask about the the interface,
哦，抱歉，我想问一下接口的事，
so the interface is just like xv6, right,
所以接口像 xv6 一样，是吗，
so the processes they have to put something in some register
进程必须把一些东西放在某些寄存器上，
and then they call the ecall or whatever it is.
然后它们调用 ecall ，或者不管它是什么。
Yeah, yeah I'll talk a little bit more about this,
是的，我会再多说一点，
but it's exactly the same, there's no difference.
但它是完全一样的，没有什么不同。
Okay I see, thank you.
好的，我明白了，谢谢。
So some of the features you know already mentioned them a little bit,
一些功能已经提过了，
maybe worth talking about its multicore,
或许多核值得讨论一下，
Go with good support for concurrency
Go 对并发的良好支持，
and so you know Biscuit's multicore,
Biscuit 的多核，
in the same way that xv6 sort of has limited support for multi-core,
以同样方式， xv6 对多核的支持有限，
in this, we have
在这里，我们有
a little bit more fine-grained synchronization or coordination than actually in xv6.
比 xv6 有更细粒度的同步或协调。
It has threads you know user level threads,
它有用户级线程，
[backed] up by kernel threads,
由内核线程[提供]，
which xv6 doesn't have,
这是 xv6 没有的，
there's journal file system much higher performance,
有日志文件系统，具有更高的性能，
like think you know you'll called the ext3 paper,
你会在 ext3 论文中看到，
sort of like you know the ext3 generally file system.
就像 ext3 文件系统。
It has, you know quite reasonable, sophisticated memory system,
它有，相当合理，复杂的存储系统，
you know using VMAs,
使用 VMA ，
and you know it could support mmap and all that stuff.
它可以支持 mmap 之类的东西。
It has a complete TCP/IP stack,
它有一个完整的 TCP/IP 协议栈，
you know good enough to actually talk to other network servers across the Internet
可以通过互联网与其他网络服务器进行通信，
and it has two drivers with high performance drivers,
它有两个高性能的驱动器，
so like a ten gigabit NIC,
比如一个万兆网卡，
in the next lab,
在接下来的实验里，
you can actually implement a little driver for a very very simple NIC,
你可以实现一个非常简单的网卡的驱动，
this is a much more high performance and sophisticated driver.
这是一个更高性能和更复杂的驱动程序。
And in a pretty sophisticated this driver,
在一个相当复杂的驱动程序中，
you know more sophisticated than the VIRTIO_disk driver,
比 VIRTIO_DISK 驱动程序更复杂，
that you've sort of seen or you might have looked at in the labs.
你可能在实验里见过的。
So in terms of a user programs as I mentioned before,
那么，就我前面提到的一个用户程序，
every user program runs its own page table,
每个用户程序运行自己的页表，
user kernel memory isolated by hardware,
用户内核内存由硬件区分，
so you use a kernel bit basically,
使用一个内核位，
and every user thread has a corresponding kernel thread,
并且每个用户线程都有对应的内核线程，
so for example when a user thread makes a system call,
比如，当用户线程进行系统调用时，
it will continue running on the corresponding kernel thread,
它将继续在相应的内核线程上运行，
and if the system call blocks,
如果系统调用阻塞，
then another user thread in the same address space
那么另一个在相同地址空间的用户线程，
and the user address space might actually be scheduled by the kernel.
用户地址空间可能会由内核调度。
And as mentioned early,
如前所述，
kernel threads are provided by the Go runtime
内核线程是由 Go 运行时提供的，
and so they just Go routines.
所以它们只是 Go 协程。
So you're write ever user level,
所以，如果你编写过，
if you ever written a user level application in Go
如果你使用 Go 编写过用户程序，
and using Go and used to Go call to create a thread,
并使用 Go 调用来创建线程，
you know that those those Go routines are the ones
那些 Go 协程就是
that were actually being used by the Biscuit kernel.
Biscuit 内核使用的。
So talking about system calls,
说到系统调用，
you know this question is just asked,
这个问题是刚刚被问到的，
so it works exactly as roughly you know as in xv6,
它的工作原理与 xv6 中大致相同，
you know the user thread put arguments in registers
用户线程将参数放入寄存器中，
using a little library,
使用一个小的库，
you know that provides system call interface,
它提供了系统调用接口，
then the user threads executed SYSENTER call,
然后用户线程执行 SYSENTER 调用，
you know this Biscuit runs on an x86 processor
Biscuit 在 x86 处理器上运行，
not on the RISC-V processor,
而不是在 RISC-V 处理器上，
so the assembly instructions for actually Intel system kernel
x86 系统内核中的汇编指令
are slightly different than on the RISC-V on the RISC-V,
与 RISC-V 上的略有不同，
but you know roughly similar similar to RISC-V,
但是与 RISC-V 类似，
and then control passes to the kernel thread,
然后控制权传递给内核线程，
that was running that user thread,
运行那个用户线程的（内核线程），
and then the kernel thread executes a system call,
然后内核线程执行系统调用，
and then returns use SYSEXIT.
然后使用 SYSEXIT 返回。
So roughly similar frame,
大致相同的框架，
you know it's a trapframe that's being built and all that kind of stuff.
它建立一个 trapframe 和其他东西，
Okay.
好吗？
Any questions so far,
到目前为止，有什么问题吗，
before I dive into sort of a more sort of,
在我深入讨论更多之前，
things that were unexpected or expected,
意料之外和意料之内的东西，
but we're a little bit more challenging than were different,
但我们会有更多不同的挑战，
that I think it would go in the xv6.
我想与 xv6 比起来。
I have a question,
我有个问题，
I guess, I think,
我想，我认为,
Go wants you to use channels more than mutex locks,
Go 希望你更多地使用管道而不是互斥锁，
I guess, so would you like, would there be like,
我想，会不会是，
what the design of somethings in xv6 be like,
xv6 中某些东西的设计，
could use as channels instead of holding a lock for something.
可以使用管道，而不是持有锁。
Yeah,, there's a great a great question,
是的，这是一个很好的问题，
so we I'll come back to it a little bit again,
我会在再次回到这个问题上，
further down
再往下看，
and we have some slides
我们有几张幻灯片，
about what features of Go did we use in Biscuit,
关于我们在 Biscuit 中使用了 Go 的哪些特性，
but you know the the [] we didn't have any of using channels that much,
但是，我们没有使用很多的管道，
we mostly use locks and condition variables.
我们主要使用锁和条件变量。
So in some sense closer to like a way xv6 looks,
所以，跟 xv6 的方法很像，
than actually a one you would do then you would do with channels,
而不是使用管道的，
we did experiment actually with designs of the file system
我们进行了文件系统设计的实验，
that were much more channel heavy,
对它使用更多的管道，
and it didn't work out great,
结果不是很好，
and we got bad performance,
并且我们得到差的性能，
so yeah we switched back to sort of more a sort of simple style of synchronization
所以，我们又换回了一种更简单的同步方式，
xv6 does or Linux uses.
xv6 或 Linux 使用的那样。
Okay, so you know a couple sort of a little puzzles or implementation challenges
好的，这里有几个难题或挑战，
as we went through,
在我们实现的过程中，
one, we gotta get to runtime to work on the bare-metal
第一，我们必须让运行时在裸机上运行，
and you know that required you know wanted to
这需要，你想要，
make of course like zero modifications to the runtime where as little as possible,
对运行时进行零修改，尽可能少地修改，
so that you know Go come out with a new version of the runtime,
让 Go 有新版本的运行时，
we could just use it.
我们可以直接用它。
In fact, you know through the years,
事实上，多年来，
you know that we worked on this, where the code worked on this,
我们在做这件事，代码也在做这件事，
we upgraded the runtime many you know number of times.
我们升级了运行库很多次。
And that was turned out to be a good thing,
这是一件好事，
and it turned out,
事实证明，
they were not to be too difficult to actually to get to work on the bare-metal.
它们并不是很难在裸机上工作。
You know Go in general is designed pretty carefully
Go 是精心设计的，
to sort of be mostly OS agnostic,
对操作系统是不可知的，
because they want to be able to run into many operating system,
因为它们希望能够运行在多个操作系统上，
so it doesn't rely on a ton of OS features.
所以，它不依赖于大量的操作系统功能。
And we're basically emulated the features that actually needed,
我们基本上模拟了需要的功能，
and mostly those are the features,
大多数这些功能，
that actually just get off the Go runtime to get started
使 Go 运行时可以开始运行，
and once it started, it runs just happily.
一旦启动，它就会继续运行。
We have sort of range that Go routine run different applications,
我们有一些 Go 协程运行不同应用程序的范围，
normally in Go program correct, you know one single application,
通常在 Go 程序中，一个单一的应用程序，
and here now we're using Go routine thread
这里，我们使用 Go 协程，
around different user, different user applications.
在不同的用户应用程序之间。
And but the user applications have to run with different page tables.
但是用户应用程序必须与不同的页表一起运行。
And the little you know [] here is that
这里的[]是，
you know the we don't control or Biscuit doesn't control the scheduler,
我们或 Biscuit 不能控制调度器，
because we're using the Go runtime unmodified,
因为我们使用的是未修改的 Go 运行时，
so we're using the Go runtime scheduler,
所以我们使用的是 Go 运行时调度器，
and so in the scheduler, we can't switch page tables.
所以在这个调度器中，我们不能切换页表。
So what xv6 in basically what Biscuit does is very similar to xv6,
在 Biscuit 中所做的与 xv6 很像，
it actually switches page tables,
它切换页表，
when it changes from kernel to user space or the other way around.
当它从内核空间切换到用户空间，或者相反。
So when entry and exit of the kernel, switch page tables.
所以当进入和退出内核时，切换页表。
And that means like in xv6
这意味着像在 xv6 中，
and then when you need to copy data
当你需要复制数据，
from user space to kernel space or the other way around,
从用户空间到内核空间或相反时，
you have to do that sort of using those copyin and copyout functions,
你必须使用 copyin 和 copyout 函数，
that we also have in xv6,
我们在 xv6 中已有的，
basically you do the page table walking software.
你需要做页表扫描软件。
Another issue of challenge where little challenge was device interrupts,
另一个挑战是设备中断，
and Go runtime normally runs in user mode,
Go 运行时通常在用户模式下运行，
you know it doesn't really get interrupts from the hardware,
它不会收到来自硬件的中断，
but we're using it on the bare-metal
但是我们在裸机上使用它，
and so we're going to get interrupts,
所以我们会得到中断，
time clock interrupts, interrupt from the network driver,
时钟中断，网络驱动中断，
interrupt from the disk driver etc, you know from the UART.
磁盘驱动中断，比如 UART 。
And so we need to deal with that
所以我们需要解决这个问题，
and and there's also no notion in Go
而且在 Go 中也没有这个概念，
you know for switching off interrupts while holding a lock,
在持有锁的同时关闭中断，
because just show up user applications,
因为它只显示用户应用程序，
and so we have a little bit careful how to actually write a device interrupt
所以，我们需要对如何写入设备中断很小心，
and basically the way we did it is,
我们的做法是，
we do almost nothing in the device interrupt,
我们在设备中断时几乎什么都不做，
we don't take any locks out,
我们不使用任何锁，
basically we don't allocate any memory,
我们不分配任何内存，
the only thing we do is
我们唯一做的是，
basically sending a flag somewhere that wasn't interrupted
把标志送到某个没有被中断的地方，
and then wake up a really functional Go routine to actually deal with the interrupt.
然后唤醒一个有效的 Go 协程来处理中断。
And that Go routine, of course you can use all the Go features that it wants.
而那个 Go 协程，当然你可以使用它的所有 Go 的功能。
Because it does run in the context of an interrupt handler,
因为它在中断处理程序的上下文中运行，
just it runs in the context of normal normal Go routine.
只是在正常的 Go 协程中运行。
Then one thing that surprises, it was a bit of surprise,
还有一件令人惊讶的事，
you know the first three things were completely anticipated,
前三件事是完全预料到的，
that we have to deal with when a building Biscuit,
当构建 Biscuit 时，我们必须要处理的，
the hardest one that actually had suprised us,
最让我们惊讶的一件事，
and we learned a lot about,
我们学到了很多，
it was this puzzle of heap exhaustion.
就是堆耗尽的难题。
So I'm going to talk mostly for a little while about heap exhaustion
所以，我将主要讨论堆耗尽的问题，
and you know what it is, you know how it comes about
它是什么，它是怎么来的，
and how we solved it,
以及我们是如何解决它的，
but maybe before diving into that,
但是在深入讨论这个问题之前，
any any questions so far?
到目前为止，有什么问题吗？
So, [] clear.
好的，都清楚了。
Okay, so let's talk a little bit about heap exhaustion,
好的，那么让我们来讨论一下堆耗尽的问题，
I'm not going to go with full depth was in the paper,
我不打算全面深入地讨论论文中的内容，
but at least gives you a flavor of what the problem is.
但至少让你对问题有所了解。
So in the heap exhaustion,
所以，在堆耗尽的情况下，
you know let's say the blue box here is the kernel again,
让我们再次假设这里的蓝框是内核，
and you know the kernel has a heap,
内核有一个堆，
from which delegates dynamically memory,
是从动态内存中分配的，
in xv6, we don't have such a heap,
在 xv6 中，我们没有这样的堆，
because we don't have a memory allocator in the kernel,
因为我们在内核中没有内存分配器，
everything statically allocated,
所有东西都是静态分配的，
but any other kernel we'll have a heap,
但是任何其他内核中，我们都会有一个堆，
so you can call malloc, you know and free in the kernel.
你可以调用内核中的 malloc 和 free 。
And you know the things that actually get allocated on the heap,
这些东西实际上是在堆中分配的，
for example you know socket objects or file descriptor objects or process objects,
比如，套接字对象，文件描述符对象或进程对象，
struct proc, you know struct fd,
proc 结构体， fd 结构体，
all the structures that we basically statically allocated in xv6,
所有我们在 xv6 中静态分配的结构体，
normal kernels, they dynamically allocate them,
一般的内核，它们会动态分配它们，
so when you open the new file descriptor,
所以，当你打开新的文件描述符时，
there will be a file descriptor object allocated in the heap.
堆中将分配一个文件描述符对象。
And so, then the problem is,
所以，问题是，
if you're running many applications,
如果你运行多个应用程序，
you know they might open many file descriptors, may have many sockets,
它们可能会打开很多文件描述符，很多套接字，
and they sort of start filling the heap basically slowly,
它们开始缓慢地填满堆，
and so the issue is that,
所以问题是，
at some points, like the heap full,
在某个时刻，比如堆满了，
there's no space anymore for allocating a new object
没有空间用于分配新对象，
or when an application asks for example opens a new file descriptor
或者当应用程序请求打开新的文件描述符时，
and there's like you know new process, like there's new fork,
有新的进程，新的 fork ，
and the kernel wants to allocate a struct proc
内核想要分配一个 proc 结构体，
and heap used like there's no space anymore.
而堆已经没有空间了。
And what did you do that,
然后你怎么做，
you know what is you know,
你做什么，
how do you deal with that particular case,
你怎么处理这个特殊的情况，
and this is typically,
这通常，
you know this is maybe in common cases does not show up that often,
可能在通常情况下，不会经常出现，
but like if you're pushing machine hard,
但是如果你重度使用机器，
you have a couple heavy consumer processes running user level processes,
你有几个重度的使用者进程运行用户级进程，
you might end in this situation,
你可能会遇到这种情况，
where basically in all the available memory is in use
所有可用内存都在使用，
and your heap is just full.
你的堆已经满了。
And no processes calling free yet,
而且没有进程调用 free ，
you know because they're all running
因为它们都在运行，
and trying to allocate more resources for their for their particular jobs.
并试图为它们的工作分配更多的资源。
So all kind of kernel face this problem,
所以，所有内核都会面临这个问题，
when it like C kernel or Biscuit or anything
不论是 C 内核或 Biscuit 或其他任何东西，
and any kernel must solve this particular problem.
任何内核都必须解决这个问题。
The reason they they sort of showed up for us
它们之所以出现在我们面前，
as a serious issue in Biscuit
作为 Biscuit 中的一个严重问题，
was because in many kernels the,
是因为在许多内核中，
you can return an error on malloc,
你可以在 malloc 上返回错误，
in fact the xv6 does that, right, once in a while,
xv6 偶尔会这么做，
but you know in Go runtime,
但是在 Go 运行时中，
when you call new to allocate a Go object,
当你调用 new 来分配 Go 对象时，
there's no error condition, new succeeds,
没有错误条件， new 就成功了，
and so there's no way to fail it.
所以没有办法让它失败。
So let's talk a little bit about possible ways to solve this problem,
所以让我们讨论一下解决这个问题的可能的方法，
the, you know we've seen it actually xv6 once in a while,
我们偶尔会在 xv6 上看到它，
like if you remember the bcache,
如果你还记得 bcache ，
if xv6 can't find a new block you know to,
如果 xv6 找不到新的块，
a free block to use for storage a disk block in,
一个空闲的块来保存磁盘块，
actually sometimes just panics.
有时只是抛出 panic 。
You know this clearly is a completely undesirable solution
这显然是一个完全不期望的解决方案，
and it's not a real solution,
也不是一个真正的解决方案，
so why we call it a strawman solution.
所以我们称为 strawman 解决方案。
The other strawman solution is to,
另一种 strawman 解决方案是，
when you call, let's say you allocate a new piece of memory,
当你调用，比如分配一块新的内存时，
you know you go to call alloc, new to actually allocate it,
你调用 alloc new 来分配它，
you could actually you know wait for memory allocator,
你可以等待内存分配器，
it going to be one proposal to do,
它是一个提议，
turns out not to be a good proposal,
结果证明不是一个好的提议，
and the reason it's not a good proposal is that you may deadlock,
它不是一个好提议的原因是，你可能会陷入死锁，
you know, assume the following scenario,
假设下面的场景，
you're holding some,
你持有一些，
let's say the kernel has one big kernel lock,
比如，内核有一个很大的内核锁，
and you call malloc, you waiting the memory allocator,
然后调用 malloc ，等待内存分配器，
then basically no other process can run.
那么就没有其他进程可以运行了。
And you would have a deadlock have in your next process,
你的下一个进程中会有死锁，
that would actually try to run for example to free some memory,
它尝试运行，比如释放一些内存，
you know couldn't run, actually deadlock.
不能运行，其实死锁了。
Of course, this is,
当然，这是，
if you have a big kernel lock, there's an obvious problem,
如果你有一个很大的内核锁，这是一个明显的问题，
you know, but even if you have a very small, a fine-grained locking,
但是即使你有一个非常小的，细粒度的锁，
it is easy to run in a situation,
它很容易运行到这种情况，
where basically the person or the process that's waiting in the allocator is holding some lock,
等待分配器的进程持有某种锁，
that somebody else needs to actually free the memory,
而其他进程需要释放内存，
and that can get you basically this deadlock situation.
这会导致你陷入死锁。
And so we're going strawman free is to basically fail,
所以我们知道 strawman free 失败了，
or when you there's no memory anymore,
或者当不再有内存时，
alloc returns like no pointer, you check with no pointer,
alloc 返回没有指针，检查没有指针，
it's no point you fail use a [].
你不能使用[]来失败。
But [] is actually not that straightforward,
但是[]并没有那么简单，
you know the process might actually have allocated memory already,
进程可能已经分配了内存，
you need to get rid of that,
你需要扔掉它，
you may have done some partial disk operations,
你可能已经执行了部分磁盘操作，
like for example if you do a multi steps,
比如，如果你执行多个步骤，
you know partial operation maybe have done some of it, but not all of it,
部分操作可能完成了部分，但不是全部，
you have to bail out of that.
你必须跳出困境。
And so, it turns out to actually get very very hard to get right.
所以，要做对是非常困难的。
In sort of interesting, you know when digging into this
有趣的是，当你深入研究这件事时，
and trying to think about how to solve this problem,
考虑如何解决这个问题，
Linux uses both of these solutions.
Linux 使用了这两种解决方案。
And you know both actually have trouble or problems,
这两种都有麻烦或问题，
and indeed kernel developers actually have difficulty to actually get this all straight,
事实上，内核开发人员很难弄清楚这些，
if you're very interested in this
如果你对这个很感兴趣，
and you want to see some interesting discussion about this,
并且想看一些有趣的讨论，
google for "too small to fail"
在谷歌上搜索 too small to fail，
and there's a little article that talks about some of these complications,
有一篇文章谈到了其中的一些复杂情况，
you know free memory or waiting in the allocator,
释放内存或等待分配器，
and the problem that can cause.
以及可能导致的问题。
Now it turns out, for us,
现在，对我们来说，
you know so strawman 2 be the solution,
strawman 2 就是解决方案，
that you could imagine doing,
你可以想象到，
but then for us,
但是对于我们来说，
just as mentioned earlier, this was not possible,
就像前面提到的，这是不可能的，
because new just cannot return, cannot fail,
因为 new 不能返回，不能失败，
it just always succeeds,
它总是成功的，
so we've got a range in some way that this cannot happen.
所以在某种程度上，这种情况不会发生。
Plus neither of these two solutions actually particular ideal,
另外，这两种解决方案都不是特别理想，
so we wanted to come up with something that was potentially better.
所以我们要想出一些更好的东西。
Any questions so far, about the setup around heap exhaustion,
到目前为止，关于堆耗尽的设置，有什么问题吗，
before I talk about like how the way Biscuit does it.
在我谈论 Biscuit 是怎么做的之前。
This problem makes sense?
这个问题能理解吗？
I'll interpret the signings as yes, then keep going,
我理解为“是的”，然后继续，
but figure to interrupt anytime.
但可以随时可以打断。
Okay, so what is the Biscuit solution,
好的，那么 Biscuit 的解决方案是什么，
yeah, as a high level of the Biscuit solution is like almost straight forward,
从高层级来看， Biscuit 的解决方案几乎是直截了当的，
what basically does,
它所做的是，
like when you execute a system call like say you read or fork,
当你执行系统调用比如 read 或 fork ，
before jumping actually into the fork system call,
在进入 fork 系统调用之前，
right at the beginning of the fork system call,
在 fork 系统调用的开始的地方，
if you know like in a system call scheduler in xv6,
比如 xv6 中的系统调用调度器，
then first thing it does actually calls reserve,
然后，它做的第一件事就是调用 reserve ，
and it basically reserves enough memory,
它保留了足够的内存，
to be able to execute the system call.
以便能够执行系统调用。
So there's a free memory enough
所以有足够的空闲内存，
that actually whatever on memory that actually the system call needs,
无论系统调用需要的内存是什么，
the reservation will be big enough that actually and will succeed.
保留会足够大，也会成功。
So, so once the system call goes off
所以，一旦系统调用开始，
and actually successful in reserving memory,
并且成功地保留了内存，
it will actually run all the way through
它会一直运行，
and we were never with the problems,
我们不会再遇到这个问题，
that there won't be enough memory or heap exhaustion.
这里没有足够的内存或堆耗尽。
And if there's not enough memory,
如果没有足够的内存，
at the point you want to do the reservation,
在你想要预留的时候，
then basically just wait here,
那就在这里等待，
but at the beginning of the system call,
但是在系统调用开始时，
the system call doesn't hold any locks,
系统调用不持有任何锁，
doesn't hold any resources yet,
没有持有任何资源，
so it actually is perfectly fine,
所以它是非常好的，
you know wait there, no risk of deadlock.
在这里等待，没有死锁的风险。
And while it's waiting,
当它在等待的时候，
you know it can of course be doing, it can call,
它当然可以做，它可以调用，
kernel can actually evict cache,
内核可以驱逐缓存，
you know try to reduce the, basically make free up heap space,
尝试减少，释放堆空间，
maybe as you seen,
也许像你看到的，
maybe kill a process that to force you know memory actually be freed.
也许会杀死一个进程，强制释放内存。
And then once you know memory is available
然后一旦内存可用，
and the kernel decides well you know I can meet a reservation,
内核决定，可以满足预订，
then it will let the system call basically goes off and runs,
然后它会让系统调用开始并运行，
and basically executes whatever it needs to be done
然后执行它需要做的任何事情，
and then at the very end, when the system call goes down,
然后在最后，当系统调用完成时，
it's like, okay, I'm done,
它说，好的，我完成了，
and all the memory that was reserve basically comes back to the pool,
所有保留的内存都回到池中，
available for subsequent system calls.
可用于后续的系统调用。
And there's a couple of nice properties about this particular solutions,
这个解决方案有几个很好的特性，
there's no checks necessary in the kernel itself,
内核本身不需要检查，
like you never have to check whether memory memory allocation can fail,
你永远不需要检查内存分配是否会失败，
which is particularly in our case good,
这在我们的情况下很好，
because you know Go, it can't fail.
因为 Go 是不会失败的。
There's no error handling code and necessary at all,
这里不需要错误处理代码，
and there's no risk for deadlock,
而且没有死锁的风险，
because you're avoiding in the very beginning without,
因为你在一开始就避免了，
when you actually hold no locks.
没有持有锁。
Of course, you know there's all wonderful well,
当然，有很多很棒的，
the only thing is like how there's a challenge,
唯一的问题是一个挑战，
of course, how you do the reservation,
你怎么做预留，
how do you compute,
你怎么计算，
you know, how much memory a system call might need to to execute it.
系统调用需要多少内存来执行它。
And so now we have a puzzle.
所以现在我们有了一个难题。
And you know it's important that the amount you reserve,
你保留的数量是很重要的，
one, one you could do is
你可以做的一件事是，
you can reserve half memory or something like that,
你可以保留一半的内存或类似的东西，
some ridiculous amount of memory for every system call,
对每个系统调用来说都是夸张的内存量，
but that means you limit the number of system calls you can execute concurrently,
但也这意味着你限制了可以并发执行的系统调用的数量，
so you want to sort of do a pretty good job
所以你想在某种程度上把工作做得很好，
and actually computing bound of the amount of memory
计算出内存量边界，
that the system call might need.
系统调用可能需要的（内存量）。
So, the way, we ended up doing this,
所以，我们做这件事的方式，
you know turned out like sort of high-level language help us here,
是高级语言帮助我们的，
turned out like Go is actually pretty easy to static analyze,
Go 是很容易在进行静态分析的，
in fact Go runtime and Go infrastructure ecosystems
事实上， Go 运行时和 Go 基础架构生态系统
comes with a whole bunch of packages to analyze Go code.
附带了很多用于分析 Go 代码的软件包。
And we use those packages basically to compute
我们使用这些软件包来计算
the amount of memory that the system call needs,
系统调用需要的内存量，
so you can think about the,
所以你可以考虑，
let's say you have a read system call, right,
比如，你有一个 read 系统调用，
you know you know we could look at the call graph of the system call,
我们可以查看系统调用的调用图，
you know calls the function f, calls the function g, calls the function h, blah blah blah,
调用函数 f ，调用函数 g ，调用函数 h ，等等，
might continue a whole bunch,
可能会有很多，
and you know at the end of system call,
在系统调用结束时，
it [binds] to [stack] again,
它再次[绑定]到[堆栈]，
and then goes back to return to user space.
然后返回到用户空间。
And basically what we can do is
我们能做的就是，
like you know allocate you know or figure out what the maximum depth,
分配，或者计算出最大深度，
you know of this this call graph is,
关于这张调用图，
at any particular time,
在任何时间，
and then basically for that maximum depth,
然后对于这个最大深度，
you know compute how much you know live memory each of these functions need,
计算出每个函数需要多少实时内存，
so if this function calls new, you know that will allocate memory,
所以，如果函数调用 new ，分配内存，
you know we know what kind of objects there are,
我们知道这里有什么类型的对象，
there's a high level language,
我们使用高级语言，
so we can compute the size of that object is,
所以我们可以计算出对象的大小，
we can just add them up and it gives us some number s,
我们可以把它们加起来，得到一个数字 s ，
that says like the total amount of memory or the maximum amount of memory,
也就是说，内存总量或最大内存量，
that can be live at any particular point of time for that call graph.
那个调用图可以在任何时间活动。
And the reason is you know it's slightly tricky,
原因是，这有点棘手，
it's not as simple as this,
它不是这么简单的，
because for example a function h might allocate some memory,
因为，比如函数 h 可能分配了一些内存，
and then pass back to g,
然后传递回 g ，
and so you know h finishes,
所以 h 结束了，
and but you know g actually you know gets the memory that h is allocated,
但是 g 得到了 h 分配的内存，
and this is called escaping,
这称为逃逸，
the memory escapes from you know from h to g
内存从 h 逃逸到 g ，
it turns out, there are standard algorithms were doing sort of this escape analysis
有一些标准算法做这种逃逸分析，
to see determine which variables escape to the callers,
确定哪些变量逃逸到调用方，
and in that case,
在这种情况下，
you know basically whatever memory was allocated by h and that's still alive,
无论 h 分配的是什么内存，它仍然是活动的，
we have to add to whatever g is,
我们必须加上 g 的，
so you know we have to be added into s.
所以我们必须加到 s 中。
A quick question about this,
关于这个，我有一个简短的问题，
so let's assume more in some function,
所以让我们在一些函数中做更多假设，
depending on different workloads that the function is expected to have,
根据函数预期的不同工作负荷，
there might be different memories memory amounts allocated,
可能分配了不同的内存量，
so what is there like a worst-case, what memory allocation process.
那么是否有内存分配进程的最坏情况？
Yeah, that's basically it's sort of conservative scheme correct,
是的，这是一种保守的方案，
and we we computed, the tool computes,
我们计算，这个工具计算，
basically a worst possible depth of function calls.
最坏的函数调用深度。
And you know for that the worst-case,
从最坏的情况来看，
analysis how much memory that reaches system call might need,
分析系统调用可能需要多少内存，
in practice, it might need, there system call might need a lot less,
在实践中，系统调用可能需要少得多，
but you know for you know to be conservative,
但是为了保守，
we have to allocate the work we plan for the worst case.
我们必须为最坏的情况分配打算。
And so we've come to a couple of important points here,
所以我们在这里谈到了几个重要的观点，
because you know some system calls for example executive for loop,
因为，一些系统调用比如执行 for 循环，
that's depended on argument to the system call, right,
这取决于系统调用的参数，
so you can't actually statically figure out what the bound is,
你实际上不能静态地计算出界限是什么，
and so a number of cases we annotated the code
所以，在很多情况下，我们对代码进行了注释，
to say well this is the maximum bounds of this loop,
表示这是循环的最大界限，
and you can assume it's no more than that,
你可以假设不会超过这个，
and use that to actually compute this number s.
并用它来实际计算这个数字 s 。
Similarly you know, for example if you have a recursive function,
同样地，如果你有一个递归函数，
you know who knows how deep the recursion is, right,
谁知道递归有多深，
and that might also be a dependent
这也可能依赖于
on a dynamic variable or an argument to a system call.
动态变量或系统调用的参数。
In fact, you know we you know we treat Biscuit in some places
事实上，我们在某些地方处理 Biscuit ，
basically avoid recursive function pass,
避免了递归函数传递，
so actually it was possible to do this, you know do this kind of analysis.
所以做这个分析是可能的。
So this kind of analysis not for free,
所以这种分析不是免费的，
it's not completely automatic,
它不是完全自动的，
it takes a couple days of work you know for this case,
对于这种情况，它需要几天的工作，
you know Cody to go through look at all these loops and and annotate.
Cody 查看所有这些循环，然后注释。
You know there are a couple others Go specific issues,
还有一些 Go 的具体的问题，
that you have to deal with
你必须处理，
like slice, you know they might double in size,
比如切片，它们的大小可能会翻倍，
if you add an element to slice
如果您在切片中添加一个元素，
and so we imitate the slices which maximum capacity,
那么我们模仿最大容量的切片，
but I use all sort of doable for a couple days work,
但是为了让这些可行用了很多天的工作，
and you know using this tool,
使用这个工具，
then you can get a number out there is reasonable good,
你可以得到一个合理的数字，
in terms of computing on maximum amount of memory
在计算最大内存量方面，
that a particular system call needs.
系统调用所需的（最大内存量）。
And so this is basically how
所以这就是
you know we basically Biscuit solves this particular problem.
Biscuit 解决这个问题的方式。
Oh, sorry, what else are people using this tool for,
哦，抱歉，人们还用这个工具做什么，
like they're not, they're not building a kernel,
比如，他们不是在构建内核，
what are they using it for?
他们用它做什么？
Over static analysis package.
通过静态分析软件包。
Yeah.
是的。
Go compiler internally uses it for all kinds of optimizations,
Go 编译器使用它进行各种优化，
you know to and do static analysis,
做静态分析，
Go go to figure out the best way to for the best way to compile it.
Go 找出最好的方法来编译它。
I see, I see, okay, thank you.
我明白了，好的，谢谢。
So this is one of the cool things about this package,
所以这是这个软件包最酷的地方之一，
you know the compiler happens to use,
编译器可以使用，
you know what we could do.
我们可以做什么。
We'll see later on, we also use it for a couple other features.
我们稍后会看到，我们还会使用它的其他几个功能。
It's very convenient to have.
这是非常方便的。
Okay.
好的。
Okay, turns to the implementation,
好的，转到实现，
you know basically basically very similar to other kernels
与其他内核非常相似，
or like you know xv6, except more high performance.
或者像 xv6 ，除了更高的性能。
You know what we adopted
我们采用了
many of the optimizations or cleverness that the Linux kernel has,
很多 Linux 内核拥有的优化或智慧，
at least the system calls that we were trying to implement,
至少在我们试图实现的系统调用上，
you know use large pages for kernel text to avoid TLB cost,
对内核文本使用大页面，以避免 TLB 开销，
we have per-CPU NIC transmit queues to avoid synchronization between port,
我们有每个 CPU 的网卡传输队列，以避免端口之间的同步，
we have RCU,
我们有 RCU ，
I will talk a little bit more about the directory cache,
我会更多地讨论目录缓存，
which is basically lock free or read lock free directory cache,
它是无锁或无读锁的目录高速缓存，
at the end of the semester, we'll talk about RCU in more detail,
在学期末，我们将更详细地讨论 RCU ，
but you know, this could have some too,
但是，这里会有一些，
you know sort of the usual type of optimization,
一种常见的优化类型，
that actually you need to get high performance.
你需要获得高性能。
And the main lesson I think we learned is that
我想我们学到的主要教训是，
Go was not standing in the way of implementing these optimizations,
Go 并没有阻碍这些优化的实现，
so these optimizations that were implemented in C and Linux,
所以这些优化可以用 C 和 Linux 实现，
you know we've basically implemented same optimization,
我们可以实现相同的优化，
but ever implemented in Go,
但是在 Go 中实现，
and so the language itself is not a hurdle or a problem,
所以语言本身不是障碍或问题，
in fact completely conducive to actually implementing these optimizations.
实际上完全有利于实现这些优化。
There's a lot of work to implement these optimizations,
要实现这些优化需要做很多工作，
but irrespective of the language.
但与语言无关。
OK, so that brings me sort of to evaluation,
好的，这带来了某种评价，
which is really what the, the motivation of the whole paper was,
也就是整篇论文的动机，
which is like trying to handle on the benefits and the costs of high-level language,
试图处理高级语言的好处和成本，
so basically, the evaluation sort of split in two parts,
所以，评价可以分成两部分，
first talking about the benefits and then talking about the costs.
先讨论好处，再讨论成本。
So, so three questions,
有三个问题，
you know first of all, you know there's a question like didn't cheat,
首先，有一个问题，比如没有作弊，
you know maybe we avoided all the expensive high-level language features,
也许我们避开了所有昂贵的高级语言特性，
that Go offers.
Go 提供的。
Does the, second question of course does the high-level language simplify the Biscuit code,
第二个问题，当然是高级语言有没有简化 Biscuit 代码，
and would to prevent some of these exploits
并且会阻止一些漏洞，
that you know I mentioned early on in the lecture.
那些我在课程前面提到的。
So first, respect to use high-level language features,
首先，关于使用高级语言特性，
we just wanted to see
我们希望看到，
whether we were similar in terms of other big Go projects,
我们是否与其他大的 Go 项目类似，
in terms of language features,
在语言功能方面，
so that we could say,
所以我们可以说，
like all the kernel seems to be doing roughly
整个内核做了，
the same advantage of the same features in similar ways.
以相似的方式做相同功能，有相同的优点。
So we use actually the same static analysis tool or package
所以我们使用相同的静态分析工具
to basically analyze whole bunch of two big pieces of Go software that on github,
从根本上分析 GitHub 上的两个大的 Go 软件，
you know there are millions lines of code,
它们有数百万行代码，
one is you know Go runtime itself and all its packages
一个是 Go 运行时本身和所有它的包，
and the system called Moby.
另一个是系统 Moby 。
And then we just basically product for number of high-level language features,
然后，我们计算高级语言特性出现的次数，
how many times they were used for thousand lines,
每千行用了多少次，
so this graph shows that,
这张图显示这些，
as usual, on the x-axis are the language features.
x 轴是语言特性。
Basically allocations correspond to calling new
allocations 对应于调用 new ，
and so this corresponds to the memory,
这对应于内存，
that it will be dynamically allocated by the garbage collector.
由垃圾收集器动态分配。
You know maps are like hash tables, slices or dynamic arrays.
maps 对应于哈希表，切片或动态数组，
You know, here's the channels synchronization,
这是 channel 同步，
as you can see, we use it very littlely,
正如你所看到的，我们很少使用它，
but so does the Go runtime and the Moby.
但是 Go 运行时和 Moby 也是如此。
Clearly the feature that we like most,
显然，我们最喜欢的特性，
it was multi function return, being able to return multiple values.
它是函数多返回，能够返回多个值。
You know we use closures,
我们使用闭包，
we didn't use finalizer,
我们没有使用 finalizer ，
we use defer a little bit,
我们使用了一些 defer ，
you know there's a bunch of Go routines that we do create,
我们创造了很多 Go 协程，
we use interfaces.
我们使用接口。
You know type assertions to convert from one type to another,
类型断言，从一种类型转换为另一种类型，
in the type asserts matter.
关于类型断言。
And importing many packages,
并且导入很多包，
so kernel selves build out of any packages
内核本身是由多个软件包构建的，
are not like one big single program.
而不是一个大的单一程序。
So if you look at this,
所以，如果你看这个，
you know some features you know Biscuit could use less than Golang and Moby
一些功能 Biscuit 比 Golang 和 Moby 使用得少，
and sometimes you know this could lose some features more or roughly in the [],
有时可能会或多或少失去一些功能，
not not in any sort of distinctly different way.
而不是以任何明显不同的方式。
So the main conclusion from this is
所以，由此得出的主要结论是，
you know basically uses the high-level features actually Go offers,
使用了 Go 提供的高级功能，
and doesn't sidestep them to basically get good performance.
不会为了获得好的性能而回避它们。
Okay.
好的。
I have a question,
我有个问题，
how did you, how are you able to count all this,
你怎么能数得清所有这些，
did you use the static analysis tool?
你使用了静态分析工具吗？
Yeah basically use static package, static analysis package
是的，基本上用的是静态分析包，
and then wrote a little program that uses static analysis packages
然后写了一个使用静态分析包的小程序
to go over every statement in these programs
检查这些程序中的每一条语句，
and look at what kind of type of statement is.
看看是哪种类型的语句。
And then, you get the argument
然后，你可以获取参数
to see how the arguments are being used
查看参数是如何使用的，
and that gives you a sense about how,
这给你一种感觉，关于，
allows you to count these features.
允许你对这些功能计数。
Okay.
好的。
Okay, so the next thing is a little subjective,
好的，接下来的事情有点主观，
did the high-level language simplified Biscuit code?
高级语言简化了 Biscuit 代码吗？
Yeah, I think it generally did,
是的，我认为它是这样的，
and so argued with one or two examples explicitly,
所以，举一两个例子进行讨论，
but you're now having GC allocation is actually very nice,
但是你现在有 GC 分配是非常好的，
and maybe I can make the point,
也许我可以说明这一点。
if you think of xv6
如果你考虑 xv6 ，
or you do an exec,
或者执行 exec ，
on point of exec,
在执行 exec 时，
there's a lot of data structures that need to be freed or return to the kernel
有很多数据结构需要释放，或者返回到内核，
and so that later process can use,
以便以后的进程可以使用，
using garbage collector is really easy,
使用垃圾收集器很容易，
you know the garbage collector takes care of all of it,
垃圾收集器会处理所有的事情，
you know you don't really have to do much.
你不需要做太多。
So if you allocate you know free an address page,
所以，如果你分配，释放一个地址页面，
you know the VMA correspond in address space
地址空间对应的 VMA
will be automatically freed by the garbage collector too.
也会被垃圾收集器自动释放。
Yeah, so you know just that as simple,
是的，所以这很简单，
as we mentioned earlier,
正如我们前面提到的，
the multi return values were really nice in terms of programming style,
多个返回值在编程风格方面非常好，
closures were nice,
闭包也很好，
maps were great,
maps 也很好，
you know you don't have to many [],
你不需要有很多[]，
places xv6 for example,
比如在 xv6 中，
you know look up something in a linear fashion,
以线性方式查找东西，
but if you have hash tables or maps as a first class object or abstraction,
但是如果你有哈希表或映射作为第一类对象或抽象，
the programmer you know would never do that,
程序员不用再那么做，
you use map and the runtime will take care of doing everything efficiently.
你使用 map ，运行时将负责高效地执行所有操作。
So, in in fact I think qualitatively, it feels you get simpler code.
所以，我认为定性来说，你得到了更简单的代码。
But as clearly qualitatively,
但是定性的很清楚，
you know just give a little bit more of a concrete example,
举一个更具体的例子，
where really, where sort of high-level language, particular garbage collector shines is
高级语言，特别是垃圾收集器大放异彩的地方是，
when there's a lot of concurrency between,
当存在大量并发时，
when there's concurrency threads
当存在并发线程，
and threads actually share a particular shared data item.
而线程共享特定的数据项。
And so for example, here's a simple case,
举个例子，这是一个简单的例子，
you know or you can boil down this question to,
你可以把这个问题归结为，
let's say allocate somehow dynamically object like a buffer,
假设动态分配对象，比如一个 buf ，
you know fork a thread you know and that process that buffer,
fork 出一个线程，然后执行那个 buf ，
and there's another thread that also process buffer
还有另一个线程也处理 buf ，
and do something of this buffer.
并对这个 buf 执行一些操作。
When both threads are done,
当两个线程都完成时，
you know the buffer needs to be free,
buf 需要释放，
so they can be used for later later kernel operations.
让它们可以用于后续的内核操作。
And the question is like who should do this, who's in charge,
问题是，谁应该做这件事，谁来负责，
and there's a little bit difficult to coordinate in C,
用 C 来协调有点困难，
because you have to have some way of deciding that
因为你必须有某种方法来确定
actually the buffer is actually not being used,
buf 并未被使用，
if you use a garbage collector,
如果你使用垃圾收集器，
there's nothing to decide,
没有什么需要决定的，
basically both threads run when the done of the buffer,
两个线程运行，完成对 buf 的操作后，
no thread is pointing to that buffer anymore,
没有线程再指向 buf ，
the garbage collector you know will trace you know starting from the threads stacks
垃圾收集器将从线程堆栈开始跟踪，
and will never you know and will not count buffer any of the thread stacks
并且永远不会计算 buf 任何线程堆栈，
and therefore the garbage collector free the memory at some point later.
所以，垃圾收集器会在稍后的某个时刻释放内存。
And so in a garbage collector language,
所以，在垃圾收集语言中，
you don't have to think about this problem at all.
你根本不必考虑这个问题。
So you know one way you could try to solve this problem, in the kernel like C,
有一种你可以解决这个问题的方法，在 C 内核中，
so you maybe put reference counts on the objects,
所以你可以计算对象的引用计数，
the reference count, of course have to be protected by locks,
引用计数当然要用锁来保护，
perhaps were some atomic operations
也许是一些原子操作，
and then when the reference count reaches zero,
然后，当引用的计数达到零时，
then you can dereference it.
你可以取消引用它。
And it turns out,
事实证明，
like you know locks in reference counts are actually slightly expensive,
引用计数中的锁实际上比较昂贵，
if you wanna high performance,
如果你想要高性能，
you know concurrency and scale up to the number of cores
将并发性扩展到内核数，
and then actually can be a bottleneck,
那么可能会成为一个瓶颈，
then we'll see that later
我们之后会看到，
in a couple weeks we read a paper,
几周后，我们看的论文，
that actually talks about this very explicitly.
非常明确地谈到了这一点。
And so people tend to,
所以人们倾向于，
want to do high performance, get good parallelism,
想要做高性能，获得良好的并行性，
people tend to avoid them.
人们倾向于避免它们。
And in fact, in particular scenario,
事实上，在特定情况下，
we try to avoid them is like in read block,
我们试图避免它们，在读取块中，
you would like to make at least reading sort of lock free,
你希望至少在读取中是无锁的，
so you don't have to pay the cost.
这样你就不用损失了。
And so, for example, here's a code fragment, that we do that,
比如，这是我们这样做的一个代码片段，
here we have a get function,
这里我们有一个 get 函数，
basically you reads the head of a queue
用于读取队列的头部，
and returns the whatever is at the head of the queue,
并返回队列头部的任何内容，
does it basically in a lock free manner,
它是以一种无锁的方式运行的，
use atomic_load to actually read the head,
使用 atomic_load 来读取头部，
but it doesn't actually take a lock out,
但是它并没有使用锁，
then, the writer does locks out.
然后，写入使用了锁。
So this is like lock free, the writers not lock free.
所以这是无锁，而写入不是无锁。
And this is a very common style in the Linux kernel,
这是 Linux 内核中非常常见的风格，
and so the writer actually they takes the lock,
所以写入者拿到了锁，
you know whatever looks at the head,
无论查找头部的任何东西，
maybe is the pop function and pops of the head from the queue,
也许是 pop 函数，将头部从队列中弹出，
and then you know in principle you could reuse it,
然后，你可以重复使用它，
and then unlocks, when you free the head.
然后解锁，当你释放头部时。
Now again in,
现在再来一次，
you see, there's a little bit difficult,
这有一点困难，
when do you actually free the head,
你什么时候真正释放头部，
because it could be the case,
因为可能是这种情况，
that some other concurrent thread that [],
一些其他的并发线程，
you know just before you did this atomic_store,
正好在做这个 atomic_store 之前，
you know this guy actually came through
这个函数过来，
and basically got a pointer to that particular object,
得到一个指向那个特定对象的指针，
so once you're done with this atomic_store,
所以一旦你完成了这个 atomic_store ，
you can't actually free the pointer,
你不能释放指针，
because there could be another thread actually has a pointer to it,
因为可能有另一个线程有指向它的指针，
and if you free it right here,
如果你在这里释放它，
you could actually have a use-after-free bug.
你可能会有一个 use-after-free bug。
And so, and so you know we'll see in a couple lectures,
我们会在几节课中看到，
there is currently a very clever solution for this
有一种非常聪明的解决方案，
which is called read copy update or RCU,
称为读取复制更新或 RCU ，
basically what it does is
它所做的是，
defers free of memory until really knows it's safe.
推迟释放内存，直到知道它是安全的。
And it has a very clever scheme to actually decide how when it's safe,
它有一个非常聪明的方案来决定什么时候它是安全的，
but that scheme does come with all kinds of, comes with restrictions
但是这个方案有各种各样的限制，
and programmers actually have to obey some set of rules,
程序员必须遵守一些规则，
that you must follow for sort of RCU critical sections as they're called,
你必须遵循他们所谓的 RCU 临界区，
for example, you can't call just you can't call,
比如，你不能调用，
you can't go to sleep in an RCU critical section or schedule.
你不能在 RCU 临界区或调度中进入睡眠。
And so it turns out you know alrough the Linux kernel uses extremely successful,
所以，尽管 Linux 内核使用非常成功，
you know a bit error prone
但是比较容易出错，
and requires careful program to get it right.
需要仔细的程序才能正确。
And in the case of the garbage collector language like you know Go,
在垃圾收集器语言的情况下，比如 Go ，
this is a non issue,
这不是问题，
because the garbage collector will actually determine when actually something is not in use anymore
因为垃圾收集器会确定某个东西何时不再使用，
and then only then free it.
然后才会释放它。
And so there's nothing really you know there's no restrictions on the programmer,
所以对程序员没有限制，
just taken care of by the garbage collector.
只是由垃圾收集器来处理。
So that's sort of an example of
所以这是一个例子，
you know where sort of more may be qualitatively or more explicit,
在某种程度上更定性或更明确，
you can see through the advantage of a garbage collected language.
你可以从垃圾收集语言的优势中看出。
Okay, terms of the CVEs you know I sort of mentioned this already,
好的，关于 CVE 我已经提到过了，
we went through all the CVEs and inspected them manually,
我们检查了所有的 CVE 并进行人工检查，
and then try to decide whether to actually Go can fix the problem.
然后试着决定 Go 是否能解决这个问题。
There for 11 them we couldn't figure out,
有 11 个我们不能确定，
you know we looked at the fix, the patch that addresses is,
我们看了解决这个问题的补丁，
we couldn't really figure out what the outcome in Go would like
我们不能确定 Go 的结果会是什么，
or how would manifest or how we change,
或者我们如何改变，
we could see how the implement it to fix,
我们可以看看如何修复它，
but couldn't decide whether it actually Go would avoided the problem or not.
但是不能决定 Go 是否会避免这个问题。
A number of logic bugs in the CVEs
CVE 中的多个逻辑错误，
and so presumably Go you would make the same logic bugs in C
很可能 Go 也会出现与 C 一样的的逻辑错误，
and you know the outcome would be the same.
结果会是一样的。
But then there were about 40 memory safety bugs,
但是大约有 40 个内存安全漏洞，
use-after-free or double-free or out-of-bounds
释放后使用或双重释放或越界使用，
and in eight of these disappear,
这八个消失了，
because the garbage collector takes care of them
因为垃圾收集器负责处理它们，
as described in the last couple slides.
像最后几张幻灯片中描述的那样。
And in 32 cases, Go would have generated panic,
在 32 个案例中， Go 会引起 panic ，
because for example would Go outside of an array bound,
因为比如 Go 会超出数组界限，
and of course panic is not good, you know the kernel crashes,
当然， panic 是不好的，内核会崩溃，
but it's probably better than a security exploit.
但这比安全漏洞要好。
And so you know so 40 cases, you know basically the high-level language helped us.
所以， 40 个案例，高级语言帮助了我们。
Okay, so that's the qualitatively of the benefits,
好的，这就是好的方面，
so now I want to talk a little bit about the performance cost,
所以现在我想谈谈高级语言的性能成本，
the high-level language tax.
高级语言税。
Before doing that,
在做那之前，
let me ask if there's any more questions?
让我问一下是否有其他问题？
Okay, I'm going to go through them,
好的，我要讲一下它们，
I'm not sure we'll make it through all six,
我不确定能不能讲完全部六个，
because we reserve a couple minutes at least at the end,
因为我们在最后至少预留几分钟，
it's going to come back to the starting point of the lecture, today's question.
我们将回到课程的起点，今天的问题。
So to set up in terms of experiments,
所以要设置实验，
you know the Biscuit runs on raw hardware,
Biscuit 运行在裸硬件上，
so these experiments are on little physical machines, not on top of QEMU,
所以这些实验是在小的物理机器上运行的，而不是在 QEMU 上，
is a 4 core, 2.8Ghz Intel processor,
是 4 核， 2.8Ghz 的英特尔处理器，
16 GB RAM, but Hyperthreads disabled.
16GB 内存，但禁用了超线程。
We use three applications,
我们使用三个应用程序，
a webserver, a key/value store
一个 Web 服务器，一个键/值存储
and a mail-server benchmark.
和一个邮件服务器基准测试。
You know of these applications stress the kernel intensively
这些应用程序都给内核很大的压力，
and so they run execute system calls
所以，它们执行系统调用，
and the kernel must do a lot of work.
内核必须做大量工作。
And you can see that,
你可以看到这个，
because most of the time in these applications is spent in the kernel.
因为这些应用程序中的大部分时间都花在内核中。
So first question is like,
所以第一个问题是，
is Linux [even] or is Biscuit [even] in the []
Linux 或者 Biscuit 是不是，
of production quality the kernel or industrial quality kernel,
生产级别的内核或工业级别的内核，
and so what we did,
所以我们所做的是，
we compare the absolute through Biscuit and Linux,
我们通过比较 Biscuit 和 Linux ，
for Linux, we used 4.9 Linux,
对于 Linux ，我们使用的是 4.9 Linux ，
a little bit out of date now,
现在有点过时了，
because paper is of course are a couple years old again.
因为论文已经有几年的历史了。
But of course when Linux we have to disable all kinds of features
当然，当我们使用 Linux 时，必须禁用所有功能，
that Biscuit [uses] or doesn't provide I mean,
Biscuit 不提供的，
so like page-table isolation, retpoline,
比如页表隔离，轮询，
you know all kinds of you know a long list of features
各种各样的一些功能，
that actually Biscuit doesn't provide nor xv6 provides,
这些功能不是 Biscuit 所提供的，也不是 xv6 所提供的，
and we disable them on Linux
我们在 Linux 上禁用了它们，
to make the comparison as fair as possible.
以使比较尽可能地公平。
And of course you know some features are hard to disable,
当然，有些功能很难禁用，
you know we were not able to disabled,
我们不能禁用，
but you know we tried to get as close as possible.
但我们试着尽可能靠近。
And then we measured basically the throughput.
然后我们测量了吞吐量。
And as you can see, the Biscuit is almost always slower,
如你所见， Biscuit 几乎总是比较慢，
which always slower than Linux,
它总是比 Linux 慢，
you know CMailbench, you know it's about to get whatever 10%,
CMailbench 会差大约 10% ，
on NGINX a little bit more,
在 Nginx 上，再多一点，
Redis is a little bit of 10 15 percent.
Redis 是 10% 或 15% 。
But you should use these numbers very grain as result, right,
但是你应该粗粒度地比较这些数字，
because, you know they're not identical,
因为，它们不一样，
and it's not apples to apples comparison,
这不是一一对应的比较，
but they like to sort of first order
但是首先，
you know they're roughly the same ballpark at least,
它们至少是大致相同的，
you know they're not like 2x 3x 4x or 10x off,
它们不是 2 倍、 3 倍、 4 倍或 10 倍的差距，
and so you know maybe it's worthwhile to actually be able to do actually,
所以，也许真正能够做到这一点是值得的，
you know to draw some conclusions out of that.
从中得出一些结论。
So then we sort of looked at,
所以我们看一下，
like you know we look basically profile the code
我们分析代码，
and try to bucket you know the cycles that were spent by the code,
并尝试对代码所花费的周期分类，
particularly we're looking at which cycles were actually in the garbage collector,
特别是，我们关注的是垃圾收集器中有哪些循环，
which cycles were actually in the prologue function calls,
哪些周期在 prologue 函数调用中，
and prologues in Go does a bunch of work,
Go 的 prologue 做了很多工作，
you know to ensure that the stack is large enough,
确保堆栈足够大，
so you know run of the stack,
可以在堆栈中运行，
write barrier cycles, this is actually when in garbage collector mode,
写入屏障循环，这是在垃圾收集器模式时，
you know the garbage collector turns on write barriers
垃圾收集器打开写入障碍，
to basically track pointers between different spaces.
用于跟踪不同空间之间的指针。
And the safety cycles,
而安全周期，
which are safety cycles are the cycles spent on array bound checks
安全周期是在列表边界检查上花费的周期，
and things like that, no pointer checks.
诸如此类的事情，无指针检查。
And so if you look at these applications you know here the numbers,
所以如果你看这些应用程序，这里的数字，
so 3% of the execution time was actually spent in sort of GC cycles,
3% 的执行时间花在了 GC 周期上，
and I'll talk a little bit about why that's low,
我们会稍微讨论一下为什么这个很低，
but you know in this case,
但在这种情况下，
that the garbage collector running while running these applications,
垃圾收集器在这些应用程序运行时运行，
so it's not the case that we measured the applications,
所以这不是我们测量应用程序的情况，
we give so much memory,
我们提供了很多内存，
that you know just run without actually running the garbage collector,
只是运行而不需要垃圾收集器，
surprisingly actually the prologue cycles turned out to be the highest,
令人惊讶的是， prologue 周期是最高的，
and this is basically you know the way the scheme,
这就是方案的方式，
that we're using that time for checking whether the kernel stack
我们使用这些时间检查内核堆栈，
or the stack of a thread needed to
或线程堆栈，
or Go routine needed to be grown or not,
或 Go 协程是否需要增长，
and this is something that actually the Go design that point in a [],
而这是 Go 设计中的一种[]，
that it's probably easier to get lower,
它可能更容易降低，
very little time actually write barrier is,
写入屏障的时间很短，
you know 2-3% you know in the safety cycles.
有 2-3% 在安全循环中。
And so in some sense, you know there's good news,
所以在某种意义上，这是个好消息，
you are not at, you know tax is not gigantic,
你不在，（高级语言）税并不是很大，
of course this number could be much higher,
当然，这个数字可能会高得多，
because this is completely dependent on how many, how big you know the heap is
因为这完全取决于堆的数量和大小，
or live the live number of, live objects is,
或者活跃的对象的数量，
because the garbage collector will have to trace all the live objects
因为垃圾收集器必须跟踪所有活动对象
to actually determine which objects are not alive.
以确定哪些对象是不活动的。
And so if there's a lot of live objects,
所以，如果有很多活的对象，
you know the garbage collector will have to trace more objects,
垃圾收集器不得不跟踪更多的对象，
and so this completely sort of linear with the number of live objects.
所以这与活跃对象的数量完全成线性关系。
So we did some other experiments.
我们也做了一些其他的实验。
Let me zoom out a little bit,
让我稍微缩小一点，
where we basically allocate a ton of live data,
我们分配了大量的活动数据，
2 million vnodes,
200 万个虚拟节点，
think about this as 2 million inodes
可以将其视为 200 万个 inode ，
and a free the amount of heap RAM
并且释放大量的堆内存，
or change the amount of heap RAM the garbage collector has,
或者修改垃圾收集器拥有的堆内存的大小，
you know for free memory,
为了释放内存，
and then [] and then measure the cost.
然后[]，然后测量成本。
So this is the table here,
就是这张表，
we have like 640 megabytes is live data,
我们有大约 640 兆字节的活跃数据，
and there's running with different memory sizes,
使用不同的内存大小运行，
and one sizes case, there are 320 megabytes of data,
在一种大小的情况下，有 320 兆字节的数据，
so the ratio of live to free is 2,
所以活跃与空闲的比是 2 ，
you see that in that case,
你可以看到，在这种情况下，
Go does do a great imitation of [] overhead the garbage collector,
Go 很好地模仿了垃圾收集器的开销，
because the garbage collector needs to run a lot,
因为垃圾收集器需要运行很多次，
because it doesn't have much heap RAM.
因为它没有太多堆内存。
But you know if you're basically if free memories about twice,
但是，如果你有两倍空闲的内存，
you know you could buy enough memory,
你可以买到足够的内存，
that free memory twice you know that the live memory,
空闲内存是活跃内存的两倍，
then the garbage collection overhead is not actually that great, in the 9% range.
那么垃圾收集开销不是那么大，在 9% 的范围内。
So basically to keep the GC overhead like a rough [] [], around below 10%,
所以，要将 GC 开销控制在 10% 以下，
you need about three times the heap size in terms of physical memory.
就物理内存而言，你需要大约三倍的堆大小。
Any questions about this?
对于这个，有什么问题吗？
I had a question about the write barriers,
我有一个关于写入障碍的问题，
what are those, do you,
那些是什么，
is it like you said some permissions?
是不是像你说的一些权限？
You know, so if you remember the lecture for a little while ago,
如果你记得之前的课程，
the kind of Appel&Li paper paper,
那个 Appel&Li 论文，
where we talked about the to and from spaces.
在那里，我们讨论了 to 和 from 空间。
And garbage collector runs,
垃圾收集器运行，
then you have to check whether the pointers in the from space, right,
必须检查指针是否在 from 空间中，
because it's in the [from] space, you have to copy it.
因为如果它在 form 空间中，你必须复制它。
And basically that the write barrier are very similar,
基本上写入屏障类似，
and it's the same sort of type idea,
是同一种类型的想法，
where you need to check every pointer
你需要检查每个指针，
to see you actually actually point in space
查看实际指向的空间，
that actually you need in garbage collector.
垃圾收集器所需要的。
Okay.
好的。
That's write barrier.
那就是写入屏障。
Sorry, so like the free memory,
抱歉，比如空闲内存，
what is what is it exactly like how does it work,
它是怎么工作的，
that the live is more than free.
在活跃内存大于空闲的情况下。
Oh yeah, yeah, okay so you buy some amount of memory,
哦，好的，你买了一些内存，
and live memory is actually memory that was used by these vnodes,
而活跃内存是这些 vnode 使用的内存，
and then there was another 320 megabyte was just free.
然后又有 320 兆字节是空闲的。
And so when this application allocated more vnodes,
所以，当这个应用程序分配更多 vnode 时，
the first came out of the free memory,
首先来自空闲内存，
until the free memory is full,
直到空闲内存变满，
[] then concurrently the garbage collector is running.
垃圾收集器同时运行。
And, and so we're running like three configuration,
所以我们的运行方式是三种配置，
in one configuration, basically the amount of free memory twice as the live memory,
在一种配置中，空闲内存量是活动内存的两倍，
and so that means that the garbage collector has a lot of heap RAM
这意味着垃圾收集器有很多堆内存，
to do sort of concurrently while running with the application.
在与应用程序一起运行的同时执行某种操作。
And if there's a lot of heap RAM,
如果有很多堆内存，
in this case where free memory,
在这种情况下，是空闲内存，
then you know the garbage collection overheads are not that high,
那么垃圾收集器的开销就没有那么高，
over there around 10% instead of 34%.
在那里是 10% 左右，而不是 34% 。
Okay, I see, I see, thank you.
好的，我知道了，谢谢。
Think about it like there's a little bit of slack
考虑有一些闲置空间，
you know for the garbage collector to do its work.
让垃圾收集器做它的工作。
Right, I I thought that it's like total 320, that was confused.
是的，我以为一共是 320 ，那就太迷惑了。
No, no, the total is 320 plus 640
不，总数是 320 加上 640 ，
and my last line is 640 plus 1280.
并且我的最后一行是 640 加上 1280 。
Okay, thank you.
好的，谢谢。
I'm gonna skip this,
我要跳过这个，
actually let me talk a little bit of pauses,
让我稍微说一下关于暂停，
you know this is,
你知道这是，
the Go garbage collector is a concurrent garbage collector
Go 垃圾收集器是一个并发垃圾收集器，
and short pauses stop the world for a very short period of time,
短暂的暂停让世界停下来很短的一段时间，
basically to enable write barriers
用于启用写入障碍，
and then basically the application keep on running,
然后，应用程序继续运行，
while the garbage collector doesn't work,
在垃圾收集器不工作的情况下，
and it's incremental as like the one that we discussed a couple weeks ago,
它是渐进式的，就像我们几周前讨论的那样，
where basically every call to new does a little bit of garbage collection work.
每个对 new 的调用都会执行一些垃圾收集工作。
And so every time you do a little bit of garbage collection working,
所以每次你做一点垃圾收集工作，
there's some some delay that's been cost, right.
有一些延误，有代价的。
And so we measured you know the,
所以我们测量了，
it took one application and looked at the maximum pause time,
使用一个应用程序，并查看了最大停顿时间，
so the maximum time an application can be stopped
应用程序可以停止的最长时间，
and of course the garbage collector needs to do some work.
当然垃圾收集器需要做一些工作。
And it turned out to be the max single pause 150 microseconds,
结果是最大单次停顿是 150 微秒，
that's in the case of the webserver that was using the TCP stack,
这是使用 TCP 堆栈的 Web 服务器的情况，
and basically, a large part of the TCP connection table needed to be marked,
基本上 TCP 连接表的很大一部分需要标记，
before you know continuing, that took 115 microseconds.
在你继续之前，这花了 115 微秒。
The maximum total pause time for a single Nginx http request is
单个 Nginx http 请求的最大总暂停时间是
the sum of the number of single pauses,
单个暂停次数的总和，
and the maximum pause time in total for a single request was 582 microseconds,
并且单个请求的总最大暂停时间是 582 微秒，
so [] when the request comes into the machine,
所以当请求进入机器时，
during you know there was total delay of 582 microseconds, execute that request.
在总共有 582 微秒延迟，执行该请求。
And it just happened very, very seldom,
而且这种情况非常罕见，
you know only you know point 3% requested times actually had a delay of more than 100 microseconds.
只有 3% 的请求时间延迟超过 100 微秒。
And so you know that's not good,
所以这并不好，
if you're trying to achieve like an SLA
如果你想要实现一个 SLA ，
or where basically the longest period of time of request takes you know it's small,
或者请求的最长时间很小，
but you know the, you look at you know google papers about like tail at scale,
但是你查看谷歌的 Tail at Scale 的论文，
like how long the longest request takes,
比如最长的请求需要多长时间，
you know they're talking about
他们谈论的是
the order of tens of milliseconds, milliseconds or 10 milliseconds,
几十毫秒，毫秒或 10 毫秒的量级，
and so probably the programs that these particular programs that actually have a pause
所以这些程序有最大暂停，
with maximum [] to pause for 582 microseconds,
最大的暂停是 582 微秒，
sort of within the budget.
在预算之内。
You know it's not ideal, but it's not crazy,
这不是很理想，但也不疯狂，
and so basically says that actually the,
所以基本上说，
really, what this basically says that,
这基本上说明，
the Go designers you know did actually terribly good job
Go 设计者做得非常好，
of actually implementing their garbage collector,
在实现垃圾收集器方面，
or impressively good job.
或者令人印象深刻的工作。
And this is one of those things that we've noticed while doing this project,
这是我们在做这个项目时注意到的一件事，
every time we upgraded the Go runtime,
每次我们升级 Go 运行时，
the next runtime, it came with a better garbage collector,
下一个运行时，带来了更好的垃圾收集器，
and actually these numbers got better and better.
这些数字变得越来越好。
Okay, one more through technical detail that I want to go over,
好的，我想再说一个技术细节，
so far you know like the first comparison between Linux and Biscuit,
到目前为止， Linux 和 Biscuit 之间的第一个比较，
you know it's not really fair,
这并不公平，
because Biscuit and Linux implement slightly different features,
因为 Biscuit 和 Linux 实现的功能略有不同，
so we did one more experiment,
所以我们又做了一个实验，
where we basically tried to code up two kernel paths completely identical,
我们尝试编写两个完全相同的内核路径，
evolving in Linux and in like in C and Go,
在 Linux 和类似的 C 和 Go 中，
and so we looked at the code path and sort of verify it,
所以，我们看了代码路径，并对其进行验证，
basically you know it implements exactly the same thing,
基本上它实现的是完全相同的东西，
and we look at the assembly structures,
我们看一下汇编结构，
you know to really see what what the differences are,
来真正了解它们的不同之处，
there gonna be some differences,
会有一些不同，
because Go is going to pay the safety checks,
因为 Go 要支付安全检查，
but just in terms of basic operation,
但就基本操作而言，
that at least two code paths are identical in terms of functionality.
至少两个代码路径在功能方面是相同的。
And we did that for two code paths,
我们对两条代码路径都这样做了，
you know it's difficult to do,
这很难做到，
because it's painstaking job,
因为这是辛苦的工作，
we did for two,
我们做了两个，
or Cody did actually for two.
或者 Cody 做了两个。
And then we compare them,
然后我们对它们进行比较，
and so here's results from one of them,
这是其中一个结果，
this is pipe ping-pong you know sort of test,
这是管道 ping-pong 测试，
you know ping-pong you know byte across a pipe,
ping-pong 字节在管道上通过，
and we just looked at the code path through the kernel
我们查看了通过内核的代码路径，
to actually get a byte from one end to the pipe to the other end of the pipe.
让字节从管道的一端到管道的另一端。
You know, sort of amount code in Go is like this 1.2k lines code
Go 中的代码有 1.2k 行，
and C it's 1.8k lines of code,
而 C 是 1.8k 行代码，
and there's no allocation, no GC,
而且没有分配，没有 GC ，
so those things are just a differ,
所以这些东西是不同之处，
we also looked at runtime,
我们还研究了运行时，
like where's the most time spent in both code paths,
比如在两个代码路径中花费的时间最多的地方，
you know the same top-10 instructions showed up,
同样的前十大指令出现了，
so we have some confidence that the code paths really are closer,
所以我们有信心，代码路径真的很近，
closer, you can get to make them similar.
近到可以让它们相似。
And then we looked at basically the amount of operations you can do per second,
然后我们看一下每秒可以完成的操作量，
and as you see here,
正如你在这里看到的，
basically you know Go a little slower than the C implementation
Go 比 C 实现慢一点，
and you know the ratio is about 1.15% slower.
大约慢了 1.15% 。
And, that's you know you look at the prologue/safety-checks,
你看一下 prologue/safety-check ，
you know these are all the instructions that C code does not have to execute,
这些都是 C 代码不需要执行的指令，
it turned out to be 16% more assembly instructions,
结果是汇编指令多了 16% ，
and so that's sort of roughly sort of makes sense.
所以这大概是有道理的。
So you know the main conclusion is you know Go is slower,
所以主要结论是 Go 会更慢，
but pretty competitive, you know not not ridiculously slower.
但是很有竞争性，不是慢得离谱。
And that seems in line with the early results of
这似乎与之前的结果是一样的，
where we did these Linux to Biscuit comparison directly.
我们直接将 Linux 与 Biscuit 进行比较。
Okay, so let me zoom a little bit further,
好的，让我放大更多一点，
let me skip this,
让我跳过这个，
because I want to talk a little bit about,
因为我想稍微谈一下，
this sort of the question that we asked in the beginning,
我们一开始问的这类问题，
where should one use high-level language for a new kernel.
是否应该对新内核使用高级语言。
And, maybe you know like instead of answering,
也许，不是直接回答，
I have some thoughts about this here in this slide,
在这张幻灯片里，我有一些想法，
you know there were some conclusion that we draw,
我们得出了一些结论，
and you know it's not a crisp conclusion, some considerations,
这不是一个明确的结论，一些考虑，
so maybe to take a step back and ask yourself the question,
所以也许我们应该退后一步，问问自己这个问题，
like what would you have preferred,
比如你喜欢什么，
you know, would you have preferred to write you know xv6 and the labs in C
你是更喜欢用 C 语言编写 xv6 和实验，
or would you prefer to use a high-level language for example like Go.
还是更喜欢使用类似 Go 的高级语言。
And particularly answer this question,
特别是回答这个问题，
what what kind of bugs would you have avoided,
你会避免什么样的 bug ，
and maybe you have some time during this lecture
也许你在这节课中有一些时间
to think about like what bugs you had,
来思考一下你有什么 bug ，
and I would love to hear you know what your experience,
我很想听到你的经历，
how do you think switching to a high level language
你认为切换到高级语言
would have changed your experience.
会如何改变你的经历。
Or if you have any thoughts on this question at all.
或者你这个问题有任何想法。
Let me, pause you for a little bit,
让我暂停一会，
so you can think about this and maybe chime in.
你可以考虑一下，再加入进来。
I have had a couple of times when I did the thing,
我有过几次这样做的经历，
where I create an object in a function
我在函数中创建对象，
and then return a pointer to it
然后返回指向该对象的指针，
and then I do stuff with a pointer
然后我用指针做一些事情，
and then I realized that the object is gone.
然后我意识到这个物体不见了。
Yeah, so this is a classic example of sort of use-after-free case, correct.
是的，这是一个典型的释放后使用的例子。
Yeah, the second time I realize it faster than the first time.
是的，第二次我比第一次更快地意识到了这一点。
Yeah, it's definitely true,
是的，这绝对是真的，
when you see a couple of times in those bugs,
当你看到几次这些 bug ，
here you get better at them.
你可以做得更好。
Any other thoughts on this,
还有任何关于这个的其他想法吗，
you know what the experience that people have had.
人们有过什么样的经历。
Think about your worst bugs, bugs that took most time,
想想你最坏的 bug ，花了最多时间的 bug ，
would high-level language would have help?
高级语言会有帮助吗？
I think it definitely like like some of the bugs were absolutely terrible to deal with,
我觉得有些 bug 确实很难对付，
but at the same time like in in this context,
但同时，就像在这个上下文中，
I definitely appreciated having to work with such a low-level language C,
我非常感谢能够使用如此低级的 C 语言，
because it helped me to really gain a very,
因为它帮助我获得，
a deep understanding of what's actually going on inside the operating system,
对操作系统内部的情况有了非常深刻的了解，
like how it's working with memory,
比如它是如何处理内存的，
like it it it's definitely refreshing to to
它绝对是新的，
like not have all of that abstracted away
不把所有的东西都抽象化，
and to actually see exactly what's going on.
真正看到到底发生了什么。
Yeah, it makes a lot of sense,
是啊，这很有道理，
any other, any other people have opinions on this?
还有其他任何人对此有意见吗？
I think also made a lot of bugs
我想也有很多 bug ，
in which I was writing after the end of string or something like that,
在我在字符串末尾或类似的地方写入的时候，
but then I wasn't getting any useful feedback about it
但是我没有得到任何有用的反馈，
and then very strange things happened, that I couldn't explain,
然后我无法解释的非常奇怪的事情发生了，
so yeah, I.
所以，是的，我。
That show up in lab one,
那出现在实验一中，
where there's a bunch of strange operations,
那里有很多奇怪的操作，
like when you parsing directories and things like that.
比如当你解析目录之类的东西的时候。
It showed up in multiple apps.
它出现在多个应用程序中。
Okay, I'm not surprised.
好的，我并不惊讶。
Okay, that's a great example,
好的，这是一个很好的例子，
like you know that it's very nice to actually have real string objects.
拥有真正的字符串对象是非常好的。
Something on my end is that,
我想说的是，
I I found myself lacking whenever I needed something like a map,
我发现缺少映射之类的东西，
and I just I I [] every time I needed to do for loop over something and then find.
每次我需要做 for 循环，然后查找。
Yeah.
是的。
However, I will say,
不过，我要说的是，
like coming from a high-level programming background,
来自高级编程背景，
this was my first real exposure to something like C,
这是我第一次真正接触到像 C 这样的东西，
so going of of Noah's point,
所以跟 Noah 的观点一样，
it kind of helped me to understand
它在某种程度上帮助我理解了，
really what it means that,
这意味着什么，
this code that I'm writing is actually running on the CPU
我正在编写的代码是在 CPU 上运行的，
and everything is from the perspective of the CPU.
一切都是从 CPU 的角度出发的。
Yep, any other thoughts?
是的，还有其他想法吗？
Oh, I actually remember it was specifically,
哦，我记得具体是，
the difference between safe string copy or just string copy,
安全字符串复制和字符串复制的区别，
one of them was putting, was using the null terminator,
其中一个使用空终止符，
and that was.
那就是。
Yeah, a common C bug.
是的，一个常见的 C bug 。
Well, so you know first thing you know, thanks for the input,
好吧，第一件事是谢谢你的投入，
of course we're not going to change xv6 to Go
当然，我们不会将 xv6 更改为 Go
or any high-level language exactly,
或任何高级语言，
for the reasons that you know have a number of you like Noah, Amir mentioned,
因为 Noah 和 Amir 提到的原因，
Go still hides too much,
Go 隐藏的太多了，
and you know in this particular class,
在这个课程中，
whole purpose is really trying to understand everything
整个目的是试图理解所有事情，
between the CPU and the system call interface,
在 CPU 和系统调用接口之间，
and for example Go of course hides threads,
比如， Go 隐藏了线程，
and you know we don't want to hide that,
你知道我们不想隐藏它，
we want to explain to you actually how threads are implemented,
我们想向你解释线程是如何实现的，
and so, we would not want to hide this from you.
所以，我们不想对你隐藏这个。
So certainly future years,
所以可以肯定的是，未来几年，
you know of xv6 class will keep on using C,
xv6 课程将继续使用 C ，
but if you implement a new kernel
但是如果你实现一个新的内核，
and goal is not you know educating students about kernels,
你的目标不是教育学生关于内核的知识，
but goals are I'd like to say safe, you know high performance kernel,
但目标是安全的，高性能的内核，
you know there's sort of you know somethings you conclude from this study,
你可以从这项研究中得出一些结论，
they've done and what we've done, right.
他们做了什么，我们做了什么。
Yeah, memory or performance is really paramount,
是的，内存或性能是最重要的，
you know you can't sacrifice 15%, then you should probably use C,
你不能牺牲 15% ，那么你应该使用 C ，
if you want to minimize memory use, you probably use C too.
如果你想最大限度地减少内存使用，也应该使用 C 。
If safety is important or security is important
如果安全很重要，
and probably the high-level language is the way to go.
也许高级语言就是我们要走的路。
And probably in many cases performances merely important as opposed to absolute paramount,
也许在许多情况下，性能是重要的，而不是绝对的，
and in many case,
在很多情况下，
I think you know using high-level languages perfectly reasonable thing to do for kernel.
我认为使用高级语言做内核是非常合理的事情。
Probably one thing I've learned,
也许我学到了一件事，
probably you know Cody Robert and I learned from this whole project is
也许 Cody Robert 和我从整个项目中学到的是，
like whatever programming language is a programming language,
任何编程语言都是编程语言，
and you can use it to build kernels,
你可以用它来构建内核，
you can build user applications,
你可以构建用户应用程序，
there's not really standing anything in really in a way.
在某种程度上，这并不是什么真正的阻碍。
Okay, you know I think it's time to wrap up,
好的，我觉得该结束了，
you know if you have any more questions,
如果你还有什么问题，
you know fell free to hang around and ask them,
可以随意停留并提问，
if you have to go somewhere else,
如果你要去别的地方，
good luck with finishing the mmap lab,
祝你顺利完成 mmap 实验，
and for those of you,
对于你们，
when we have to are leaving campus for Thanksgiving,
当我们要离开校园过感恩节的人来说，
safe travels and hope to see you after Thanksgiving
一路顺风，希望感恩节过后见到你，
in Monday's lecture after Thanksgiving.
在感恩节后的周一的课程中。
Thank you.
谢谢。
I was curious, how did you implement it,
我很好奇，你是怎么实现的，
it said you are doing that just on the hardware,
上面说你在在硬件上做这个，
so like when you start out, how do you start out.
所以当你开始的时候，你是怎么开始的。
You know there's basically little shim code,
这里有很少的垫片代码，
that sets up enough of the hardware,
它对硬件做足够的设置，
so that when Biscuit you know asks for,
当 Biscuit 请求，
when the Go runtime ask for memory for the heap,
当 Go 运行时请求堆的内存时，
that we can actually respond.
我们可以响应。
That was one of the main things that actually Go runtime actually relies on.
这是 Go 运行时所依赖的主要内容之一。
Right, I guess I was like you said that,
是的，我想你说的是，
you didn't use a virtual machine for that, so.
你没有使用虚拟机，所以。
We did, of course we developed most of development on QEMU
我们用了，当然大部分开发都在 QEMU 上，
and of course again we actually have to get it running on the hardware,
当然，我们还必须让它在硬件上运行，
that also costs there's a bunch of problems,
这也要解决一堆问题，
because the boot loaders are different,
因为引导加载程序不同，
there's a bunch of boot code that you actually need to write,
需要编写一系列引导代码，
you don't have to write if you run it on QEMU,
如果你在 QEMU 上运行就不用写了，
and that kind of stuff,
诸如此类的东西，
but most of the development is all done on QEMU,
但是大部分的开发都是在 QEMU 上完成的，
in fact if you want to actually show you running Biscuit on QEMU,
事实上，如果你想在 QEMU 上运行 Biscuit ，
and it looks very simple to xv6,
它看起来非常简单，类似 xv6 ，
you know the only thing it does like show prompt,
它唯一就是显示提示符，
there's no window system, nothing like that.
没有窗口系统，什么都没有。
Okay, I see,
好的，我明白了，
so like what happens if you if you make a mistake in the boot code.
所以如果你在引导代码中犯了错误，会发生什么情况。
It doesn't boot,
它不能启动，
you know basically nothing happens,
基本上什么都没发生，
you know it's completely nothing.
完全没什么东西。
How do you know?
你怎么知道？
You, you, you will know,
你会知道的，
because you know okay what will happen is because you don't see print statement,
因为你知道，因为你看不到打印的语句，
like xv6 for the first thing we print is
比如 xv6 ，我们打印的第一件事是，
like you know xv6 hello or something or xv6 booting,
比如 xv6 hello 或者 xv6 引导，
you won't see anything like that,
你不会看到这样的东西，
and so you'll see nothing,
所以你什么也看不到，
and then you'll have to track down and guess what the problem might be.
然后你必须追踪，并猜测问题可能出在哪里。
Okay, so you do it by looking?
好的，那你是通过查看吗？
Okay, little bit, you can write a [synchronously] to the UART,
好的，你可以向 UART 同步写一个，
you know you could like,
你可以比如，
you know characters you see put them in random places in the code,
你看到的字符，把它们放在代码中的随机位置，
and hope that you see something.
希望你能看到一些东西。
This is interesting, thank you.
这很有趣，谢谢。
You know.
你知道。
I wanted to ask,
我想问一下，
when you, so I know like you implemented the Go,
当你，我知道你实现 Go ，
some of the calls that Go runtime would make,
有一些调用 Go 进行时会创建，
that you cannot make,
有一些无法创建，
because you're implementing the kernel itself,
因为你正在实现内核本身，
is there any like,
有没有类似的，
did you just implement just all of that in assembly
你是不是使用汇编实现了，
or did you say okay like some of this we can still do in Go,
或者这些也可以使用 Go 来实现，
like we can bring Go a bit closer,
比如我们可以让 Go 走地更近一点，
and then do assembly only what's necessary,
然后汇编只做需要的事情，
what did you say like once the Go runtime ends like that's assembly.
你说的，一旦 Go 运行时结束，就是汇编？
You the that's where the 1500 lines of assembly came from,
这就是 1500 行汇编的来源，
in the, in Biscuit,
在 Biscuit 中，
you know that is basically the code
这基本上就是代码，
to sort of get everything ready to be actually able to run the Go runtime.
为运行 Go 运行时做好准备。
Now some of that we would have implemented C,
其中一些我们可以使用 C 实现，
but we didn't want to do that,
但我们不想这样做，
because we didn't want to use any C,
因为我们不想使用任何 C 语言，
so we're use assembly.
所以我们使用汇编。
And many of it actually required assembly,
其中许多需要汇编，
because it's in the booting part.
因为它在引导部分。
Right, but I guess some of the part, that's not the boot,
是的，但我想有些部分，不是引导，
so I I you know I know that some just you cannot avoid some boot code and assembly,
我知道有些你不能避免一些引导代码和汇编，
but could you, could you have transformed some of the assembly to Go,
但是你能不能把一些汇编改为 Go ，
or did you go to the [].
还是你做了[]。
We did a bunch of Go,
我们做了很多 Go ，
that basically runs very early on,
是在很早的时候就开始了，
you know some of the Go goes quite careful,
有些 Go 非常小心，
it doesn't do any memory allocation,
它不进行任何内存分配，
and we tried to write as much as possible Go,
我们试着尽可能多地使用 Go ，
I I can like I have to look at the code exactly
我必须看代码，
you know to be able to answer your question,
才能回答你的问题，
specifically you can look at the git repo,
具体地说，你可以看看 git repo ，
but, yeah, we tried to write everything in Go.
但是，是的，我们试着使用 Go 写所有的东西。
And then one like kind of unrelated small question I had,
然后我有一个不相干的小问题，
what does Go do with its Go routines,
Go 协程是怎么做的，
that makes it possible to run like hundred thousands of them,
使它可以运行成百上千的 Go 协程，
because you cannot just spin up a hundred thousand pthreads, right.
因为你不能起成百上千个个线程。
Yeah, it depends,
是的，这要看情况，
a lot longer
时间很长，
and so the main issue is that you need to allocate stack,
所以主要的问题是你需要分配堆栈，
and the Go runtime actually allocates stack incrementally
而 Go 运行时会递增地分配堆栈，
and so grows them dynamically as you run your Go Go routine,
随着你运行 Go 协程，它们会动态增长，
this where's prologue code is for,
这是 prologue 代码的作用，
when you make a function call,
当你进行函数调用时，
you see if there's enough space
你会查看是否有足够的空间
to actually make the function call,
来进行函数调用，
and if not, it will grow dynamically for you.
如果没有，它将为你动态增长。
And often in pthread implementations,
通常在 pthread 实现中，
allocating threads a little bit more heavyweight,
分配线程是更重量级的，
because actually for example Linux basically corresponds
因为，比如 Linux 对应，
corresponding kernel threads is actually allocated too,
对应的内核线程也要被分配，
and they tend to be more heavyweight than.
它们往往更重量级。
I see,
我明白了,
is the is the scheduling of all the Go routines done completely in user space,
Go 协程的调度是否完全在用户空间中完成的，
or does it help itself with some of kernel, so.
或者它帮助自己使用一些内核。
It is mostly done in user space.
它主要是在用户空间中完成的。
So the Go runtime allocates a bunch of kernel threads,
所以 Go 运行时分配了一堆内核线程，
you know they call them I think mthreads,
他们把它们叫做 mthreads ，
and on top of that it implements the Go routines.
在这之上，它实现了 Go 协程。
So it's so it has, like a couple kernel threads
所以它有几个内核线程，
that it shares to all Go routines based on which ones running.
它共享给所有的 Go 协程，基于正在运行的。
Yes.
是的。
Oh, that makes sense, yeah.
哦，理解了，是的。
Is there like any C C++ equivalent,
有没有类似的 C 或 C++ 的等价物，
like, could you could you do something like that to save to save some memory.
比如，你能不能做这样的事来节省内存。
Yeah people have done, you know able to manage like high performance,
是的，人们已经做到了，可以管理高性能，
you know so C libraries are thread libraries,
C 库是线程库，
that way you can create thousands of you know threads for millions of threads,
你可以为数以百万计的线程创建数以千计的线程，
you know do a similar style.
使用类似的方式。
Okay, you guys have a good break, I must head out.
好了，你们好好休息，我得走了。
You too.
你也是。
See you next week or two weeks.
下周或下两周见。
Yeah, oh.
是的，哦。
Oh, go ahead.
哦，请继续。
I'm sorry, so I have a maybe basic question about the shims
抱歉，我有一个关于垫片的基本问题，
and I guess I think also maybe,
我想我可能，
I'm just not familiar with kind of specifically what like a runtime is
还不太熟悉运行库是什么样子，
and I guess like my confusion comes from the fact,
我猜我的疑惑来自这一事实，
that like from a metal model of how xv6 and C works,
比如，在裸机器上 xv6 和 C 如何工作的，
is that C compiles C is a compiled language
C 是一种编译语言，
and so it goes directly to assembly or machine code,
所以它直接进入汇编或机器代码，
and so it kind of just runs on the CPU,
所以它像是在 CPU 上运行，
and so I guess,
所以我想，
like there is no need for a shim for like xv6 OS,
就像 xv6 操作系统不需要垫片程序一样，
but I guess my understanding is Go is also a compiled language,
但我想 Go 也是一种编译语言，
so it also goes to the assembly,
所以也会变成汇编语言，
so why is there a need for like a shim in this case,
那么为什么在这种情况下需要垫片，
why, why is there maybe is a shim for like xv6,
xv6 是否有这样的垫片，
or you know what, what is different here
或者这里有什么不同，
and why are there, why are there things that can't just be done on the CPU.
为什么有些事情不能只在 CPU 上做。
Yeah yeah, a great question,
是的，一个很好的问题，
so I think the answer to your question is that,
所以我想你问题的答案是，
the Go runtime provides all kinds of features,
Go 运行时提供了所有类型的功能，
that like you know you don't have, right,
比如你没有的，
in running when you're running C in xv6,
当你在 xv6 中运行 C 的时候，
so Go runtime provides threads,
所以 Go 运行时提供线程，
Go runtime provides scheduler,
Go 运行时提供调度器，
Go runtime provides hash tables,
Go 运行时提供哈希表，
Go runtime provides garbage collector,
Go 运行时提供垃圾收集器，
that actually needs to run at runtime, right,
这需要在运行时运行，
then there's no garbage collector in xv6,
而在 xv6 中没有垃圾收集器，
and we implement the threads,
并且我们实现了线程，
and for example to support the garbage collector,
比如，为了支持垃圾收集器，
it needs a heap you know for to allocate memory from,
它需要一个堆来分配内存，
and so like ask the operating system underlying operating system,
所以访问底层的操作系统，
so please give me you know some memories,
请给我一些内存，
that I can use it as a heap.
我可以把它当作堆使用。
And basically the shim layer implements exactly so that kind of functionality,
基本上垫片层实现了这些功能，
that the Go runtime needs to do a job at runtime.
Go 运行时在运行时要做的工作。
I see.
我明白。
Yeah, you have a slightly makes sense,
是的，你说得有点道理，
I actually a follow-up question is,
我还有一个后续问题，
maybe this is a dumb question,
也许这是一个愚蠢的问题，
but like like can we just compile to runtime down to machine code, or.
比如我们能不能编译运行时到机器代码，或者。
Runtime is compile to run.
运行时被编译为运行。
Okay.
好的。
It goes like you know the runtime itself is also compiled,
运行库本身也是编译的，
but it's like you're part of the program
但这是程序的一部分，
that needs to run always running run Go code.
在运行 Go 代码时需要一直运行。
It has to be there,
它必须在那里，
like even like C has a small runtime,
就像 C 也有一个很小的运行时，
if you think about you know we have like printf
如果你想一想，我们有 printf ，
is part of should live to C runtime,
是 C 运行时的一部分，
string operations are part of the C runtime, right,
字符串操作是 C 运行时的一部分，
they're compile too,
它们也是编译的，
but there's a bunch of small number of functions that the C runtime has,
但是 C 运行时有一些很少的函数，
but their runtime is so small compared to the Go runtime,
但是它们的运行时太小了，跟 Go 运行时比起来，
that you know have to support many more features,
支持更多的功能，
because of you know programs Go programs rely on them.
因为 Go 程序依赖于它们。
I see, I see,
我明白了，我明白了，
and I guess the last question would maybe be like,
我想最后一个问题可能是这样的，
is it it kind of sounds like that in this case,
在这种情况下，是不是有点像，
the Go runtime or like the actually the shim in this case
Go 运行时或这种情况下的垫片程序
is almost taking on some of the functionality normally,
承担了一些常用功能，
like it's almost like it's like a mini,
就像它几乎就像一个小的，
it's almost kind of like, it's like a mini OS layer,
它就像一个小的操作系统层，
like in terms that it's just like another layer
就像它是另一层，
that's performing some low-level system functionality, like reasonable.
执行一些低级系统功能。
Yeah you can,
是的，你可以，
maybe one way to think about xv6,
也许可以用一种方式来考虑 xv6 ，
it also has a very very minimal shim,
它也有一个非常非常小的垫片，
you know maybe like when the boots correct,
也许当引导的时候，
the first thing it does actually allocates some stack,
它做的第一件事就是分配一些堆栈，
so that you can actually call the C main function.
就可以调用 C 主函数了。
And you can think about that little fragment of code
你可以考虑一下这段代码，
which is only a couple statements,
它只有几个语句，
the shim layer for xv6.
就是 xv6 的垫片层。
And once you know you're through a couple of instructions,
一旦你通过了几个指令，
you're actually C code and everything is fine.
你到达 C 代码，一切都很好。
And you know the shim layer to Go runtime is slightly bigger,
Go 运行时的垫片层稍微大一些，
because there's a bunch of more features that need to be set up,
因为还有更多的功能需要设置，
before the Go runtime actually happily execute.
在 Go 运行时执行之前。
Okay, yeah that's helpful, that makes sense, cool.
好的，这很有帮助，很有道理，酷。
Thank you.
谢谢。
You're welcome.
不用谢。
Happy Thanksgiving.
感恩节快乐。
Yeah, you too.
是的，你也是。
Oh, I had a question about the ping-pong program that I forgot to ask,
哦，我有个关于 ping-pong 程序的问题忘了问，
so I remember we also did a ping-pong program in one of the labs.
我记得我们在一个实验中也做了一个 ping-pong 程序。
It was not a hundred, those a thousand lines of code, why is.
那不是一百，一千行代码，为什么是。
Because like one, I think you're referring to a lab one,
因为，第一，我想你说的是实验一，
you do the ping-pong with a byte across the pipe.
你做了 ping-pong 让一个字节通过管道。
Yeah.
是的。
Okay, so that's the user side of the benchmark,
好的，那是用户空间的基准测试，
the kernel side correctly is the other side of it,
内核方面是另一面，
and basically you know that what we did is
我们所做的是，
implement the kernel passed in identical manner.
实现以相同方式传递的内核。
Okay.
好的。
So like you know you executing the start the system call,
所以在执行系统调用，
using variables in the stack frame,
使用堆栈帧中的变量，
you know calling into looking up the pipe,
调用查看管道，
you know then running maybe the scheduler to wake up you know the receiver
然后可能会运行调度程序来唤醒接收者，
and that whole code path,
那是整个代码路径，
you know on the kernel side, we tried to implement it,
在内核方面，我们试图实现它，
identically in C and in Go.
在 C 和 Go 中是一样的。
Okay I see.
好的，我明白了。
But the benchmark is basically the same as your benchmark,
但基准与你的基准一样，
that you implemented actually in lab one,
你在实验一中实现的，
the user level side of it.
它的用户级别方面。
Right, right, okay that makes sense,
好的，这就说得通了，
so, so does that mean like,
所以，那是不是意味着，
I mean I think that if you do that in xv6
我的意思是，如果在 xv6 中这样做，
would be significantly less than a thousand lines of code,
将大大少于 1000 行代码，
if you like take all the kernel code.
如果你愿意，使用所有内核代码。
There's thousand thousand lines for assembly instructions correct,
这里有上千行的汇编指令，
so you know I I don't know I will have to look at,
我不知道，我必须看一下，
but you know you're gonna use the trapframe code,
但你会用到 trapframe 代码，
you know syscall dispatch,
系统调用调度，
going to the the fd layer, correct, the file descriptors,
到 fd 层，文件描述符，
then a little bit of pipe code,
然后是一小段管道代码，
then copyin and copyout,
然后是 copyin 和 copyout ，
then the scheduler
然后是调度器，
and then basically all [] and then bailing out again or returning.
然后再次跳出或返回。
Yeah, okay, that make sence.
是的，好的，这就说得通了。
I don't know how to talk my head on my client what code is,
我不知道怎么表示脑中的代码，
but you know.
但是你知道。